<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The righteousness of God through faith upon all without difference who believe in two sermons on Romans 3, 22 / by Nathaniel Mather ...</title>
            <author>Mather, Nathanael, 1631-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50243</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6790</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12801168</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12801168</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94055</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50243)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94055)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 362:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The righteousness of God through faith upon all without difference who believe in two sermons on Romans 3, 22 / by Nathaniel Mather ...</title>
                  <author>Mather, Nathanael, 1631-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nathaniel Hiller ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [5].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans III, 22 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Congregational churches --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94055:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94055:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> THROUGH FAITH UPON All without Difference who believe.</p>
            <p>In Two Sermons on <hi>Romans</hi> 3.22.</p>
            <p>By <hi>NATHANIEL MATHER,</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Hiller</hi> at the <hi>Princes-Arms</hi> in <hi>Leaden-Hall-Street,</hi> over againſt <hi>St. Mary Axe.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94055:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94055:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Muſt acknowledge that when I was called to Preach in that Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence where theſe Sermons were delivered, I had ſome Debates rolling in my Mind what kind of Subject I ſhould pitch upon. There were enow offered to my Thoughts wherein I might have more gratified, or at leaſt have leſs diſpleaſed our <hi>Neonomians,</hi> as they are lately named, but as truly and juſtly <hi>Semiſocinians,</hi> as the antient Church and all Poſterity ſince, hath called the off-ſpring of <hi>Pelagius</hi> his Hereſie <hi>Semi-Pelagians.</hi> But I ſaw with grief and deteſtation the Bleſſed Goſpel of our Salvation craftily and inſolently aſſaulted by them in the very Vitals and Fundamentals of it. <hi>In publico diſcrimine omnis homo miles eſt.</hi> Every Chriſtian, much more every Miniſter is ſet for the defence of the Goſpel, eſpecially at ſuch a time when the Truth labours under guileful and impetuous oppoſition. I doubted my Quiet would be attempted, and my Doctrine and Reputation would be angrily reflected on. As to the laſt, though I value it, and believe I ought to do ſo, yet I can truly ſay convictions, that I ought to ſacrifice both that and my Quiet to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the labouring Truth of God had their weight with me. My Heart hath been long fixed in this Principle, that Reputation is little to be valued, ſave only ſo far as it may be of ſervice unto Chriſt; and if he have any uſe to make of it, he will preſerve it while I walk before him in Integrity. With him I have thus left it, and having ſo done my Heart is ſecure and at reſt about it. As to my Quiet, I confeſs I do prize and love it, as remembring <hi>Prov. 17.14.</hi> and <hi>18.6.</hi> but to Maintain and Preach that Precious and Saving Truth which the Churches of Chriſt have been in poſſeſſion of ever ſince the Reformation, is not entring into contention; eſpecially when ſome abandon it, and others indeavour to wreſt it from us: And there is a contending, and that earneſtly, for the Faith once delivered to the Saints, which is a Duty. Beſides I am not far from that place, where the weary are at reſt, and the wicked ceaſe from troubling; the thoughts whereof I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs are ſweeter to me, becauſe I have very ſadning apprehenſions of the portendency of that apoſtaſie from the Truth which hath invaded ſo many of the riſing Generation, not among Conformiſts only but Diſſenters alſo.
<pb facs="tcp:94055:3"/>As to my Quiet I have this relief, that it is not in the power of any mortal to interrupt or diſturb my inward compoſedneſs of Spirit, or to lay me under any law of unquietneſs within my ſelf. I know and am aſſured, that a due exerciſe of Faith, Meekneſs, Self-denyedneſs, and ſuch like Graces, will eſtabliſh my Heart in a juſt and holy unconcerned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, though ſuch repreſentations ſhould ſtill be made of me for theſe Sermons ſake, as to fill my Friends in other Lands, to whom I am known, with trouble and conſternation. I uſe the very words of a Letter wherein I am informed that ſuch Reports have been ſent even ſo far.</p>
            <p>As to the Doctrine delivered in theſe Sermons, it hath been of uſe to me for the direction and guidance of my Heart in tranſacting with God about Pardon and Acceptance to Eternal Life. I hope it may be ſo unto others. My Hope, my Life, my Salvation, my All is therein. I have not delivered any thing but what I know and am aſſured is according to the Eternal Truth of God, and wherein I have going before me as great Lights as any that God in theſe latter Ages hath ſet up in his Church. How little, or rather nothing, I have varied in what is Printed from what was delivered in Preaching, I muſt leave to thoſe that ſhall read and did hear them. I have heard of two Paſſages that have been taxed: Of them therefore I have in a ſhort Poſtſcript given a further account.</p>
            <p>As to the Publiſhing of them in Print, if the Doctrine delivered in them be the Truth of God (as I believe it is) I need not make any Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy. Many that know me know my backwardneſs to appear in Print. Nevertheleſs in thus Publiſhing theſe Sermons my Heart condemns me not; knowing that I have therein only indeavoured to communicate in a more diffuſive and induring way that Truth, the Faith whereof I have received, and wherein I have many Years lived, and in which I hope and am perſwaded I ſhall dye; and which it is of concernment to have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and propagated. The Bleſſing of him whoſe Truth it is, go along therewith.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London, <date>
                     <hi>this 14th of the 2d Month, 1694.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Nath. Mather.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 20. line 3. for <hi>in is</hi> read <hi>is in,</hi> l. 9. <hi>a fine</hi> r. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1. l. 6. <hi>a fine</hi> f <hi>not,</hi> p. 21. l. 7. <hi>a fine</hi> r. <hi>comprizing under them his Graces,</hi> p. 25. l. 4. put the <hi>comma.</hi> after <hi>is,</hi> p. 26. l. 2. dele <hi>of,</hi> p. 27. l. 4. <hi>a fine</hi> r. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. p. 31. f. <hi>namely</hi> r. <hi>only.</hi> p. 36. l. 9. <hi>a fine</hi> f. <hi>John</hi> 15.19. r. <hi>John</hi> 15.9. p. 39. l. 14. <hi>their</hi> r. <hi>there,</hi> l. 10. <hi>a fine</hi> f. <hi>they do not</hi> r. <hi>they who do not,</hi> p. 42. l. 16. r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.28. p. 43. l. 7. f. <hi>might</hi> r. <hi>weight,</hi> f. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.8. r. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.7. p. 59. l. 20. r. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94055:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 3.22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Even the Righteouſneſs of God which is by Faith of Jeſus Christ, unto all, and upon all them that believe; for there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the firſt five Chapters of this Epiſtle, the Apoſtle ſets himſelf to declare and clear up the great Doctrine of Juſtification. And he firſt ſpeaks to it Negatively, ſhewing and evincing, <hi>that by the deeds of the Law there ſhall no Fleſh be juſtified in the ſight of God;</hi> which is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion and ſum of all his foregoing Diſcourſe, as you may ſee at the 20th. Verſe of this Chapter. Having made out that neither <hi>Jew</hi> nor <hi>Gentile</hi> can ever be juſtified by the Deeds of the Law, he declares affirmatively in the Verſe before the Text, and ſo onward, how it is then that men may be Juſtified: and he ſhews that it is by <hi>the righteouſneſs of God manifeſted without the Law,</hi> yet <hi>witneſſed to by the Law and by the prophets,</hi> that is, by the Books of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the reſt of the Old Teſtament. But how come men to be juſtified by this Righteouſneſs manifeſted without the Law, and thus wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed unto? This the Apoſtle declares in the words of the Text, telling us that <hi>this righteouſneſs is through faith upon all that beleeve, and that without difference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no need in order to what I intend, to ſay any thing for explaining of the meaning of any of the words of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94055:4"/>the Text. The Doctrine which I deſign to ſpeak to from them is plain and obvious and it is this.</p>
            <p>Doctrine, <hi>There is a righteouſneſs of God which through faith of Jeſus Chriſt is without difference unto all and upon all who believe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are theſe ſix things which offer themſelves to be ſpoken unto, for clearing this Doctrine, and making way for the Application of it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>What Righteouſneſs is this, and why is it called the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>How is it upon thoſe that believe?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>What is the meaning and import here of that Expreſſion, without Difference.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>What is this Faith of Jeſus Chriſt, and why is it ſo called?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>What reference has Faith unto this Righteouſneſs's being unto and upon Believers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>How comes all this about, and whence is it, that there is this Righteouſneſs provided, and that it is through Faith upon all without difference which believe.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Queſt. 1. <hi>What Righteouſneſs is this, and why is it called the Righteouſneſs of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To have this matter rightly ſtated in our thoughts is very uſeful and needful both for the direction, guiding and fixing of our Faith to its proper Object in its acting and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and alſo for the eſtabliſhing of our Minds in the Truth of God in this Point, leſt darkneſs and miſtakes herein ſhould occaſion our ſtumbling and the overturning of our Faith. I ſhall therefore proceed ſtep by ſtep; and deliver my ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it in five Propoſitions, in which, put together, I ſhall indeavour a clear and juſt ſtating and declaration of this Matter.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94055:4"/>
            <p>Propoſition I. <hi>This Righteouſneſs is the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and not our own.</hi> So the Apoſtle uſeth thoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions ſetting our own Righteouſneſs in Oppoſition to this Righteouſneſs, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. though there be a ſenſe wherein this Righteouſneſs may be ſaid to be ours. When I ſay it is the Righteouſneſs or Chriſt, I mean, it is the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs whereof Chriſt is the original, firſt and native Subject; it is the Righteouſneſs which he <hi>brought in,</hi> as the word is, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. a Phraſe taken from the Old Teſtament Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance wherein it was commanded that the Prieſt ſhould carry the Blood of the Sacrifice which was ſhed at the Altar of Braſs without the Tabernacle, into the Holy of Holies, and there preſent it unto God.</p>
            <p>And this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is juſtly called the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God, both becauſe it is a Righteouſneſs of Gods ordaining and providing, or deviſing, as her word is, ſpeaking of this very thing, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.14. and alſo becauſe Chriſt. whoſe it is primitively and originally, is by Nature God over all bleſſed for ever. And I think the Apoſtle delights to ſet forth this Righteouſneſs by that Epithet, that it is Gods, and of God, the more to commend it to our Conſciences and Hearts, as that which beyond all compariſon is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before, and rather choſen by us to ſtand in, than that Righteouſneſs which he calls our own.</p>
            <p>The beſt of our own Righteouſneſs is inherent in us, or wrought out by us, we are the original Subjects of it, though it be in us from God, and by his Grace. But this Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt as it is called the Righteouſneſs of God in another Senſe, and on another ground than our own Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs can be ſaid to be Gods, or of him; ſo this Phraſe is uſed of it for this end, namely to denote ſuch a tranſcendent Excellency in it, (it is an uſual <hi>Hebraiſm,</hi> to add the Epithet of God, to ſet forth a ſurpaſſingneſs in things, thus we read of the <hi>Wreſtlings of God,</hi> the <hi>Mountains of God,</hi> the <hi>Cedars
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94055:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God</hi>) that in compariſon of, and in competition with this Righteouſneſs, the Righteouſneſs of Men and Angels is to be deſpiſed and abhorred by us.</p>
            <p>Now that this Righteouſneſs in the Text is the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt, all the Circumſtances of the Text do evince, every thing which is here ſaid of this Righteouſneſs, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt which is brought in by him for us. It is a Righteouſneſs of God, it is manifeſted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Law; for the Law, that is the Covenant of Works tells us nothing of it, yet it is witneſſed unto by the Law and the Prophets, and though it was heard of in the Old Teſtament times, yet it was veiled under many ſhadows then; but now in the days of the New Teſtament it is very clearly revealed and <hi>manifeſted.</hi> It is a Righteouſneſs which is unto all and upon all without difference who do believe, and the way of its being on them is through Faith. It is that Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in which we ſtand juſtified freely of Grace, it is that Righteouſneſs which contains a price of Redemption, and which hath Propitiation or Atonement in it, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Blood of Chriſt is a part; all which are true of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt and of no other; and laſtly, it is either the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt or our own, the Scripture mentions no other Righteouſneſs that is upon us but one of theſe. But it is not our own Righteouſneſs, for our own Righteouſneſs conſiſting in our Conformity to the Law, that being to us the Rule of Righteouſneſs, we ſhould then be juſtified by the deeds of the Law, which the Apoſtle here tells us no Fleſh ſhall, for by the Law is the knowledge of Sin.</p>
            <p>Propoſition II. <hi>This Righteouſneſs of Chriſt which through Faith is upon all that believe, is the Mediatory Righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> viz. That Righteouſneſs which he as Mediator doth bring in for us and preſent unto God, and therefore in which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94055:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>he acts as Mediator between God and us. I mention this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would ſet by and ſeclude the <hi>Eſſential Righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> from being any part of this Righteouſneſs, which is upon us by Faith. By his Eſſential Righteouſneſs, I mean that perfection of the Divine Nature which we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly do alſo call Holineſs and Juſtice; and this belongs to Chriſt as he is God co-equal with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, being one of the bleſſed Perfections of the Divine Eſſence. But this Righteouſneſs cannot be ſaid to be upon us through Faith: For then we might be ſaid to be juſtified by the Righteouſneſs of the Father and of the Holy Ghoſt as we are by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt. Atonement or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God is not made for us by this Eſſential Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, nor is it brought in before God for us, nor are we ſaid to have it, nor do we ſtand accepted in it, nor is it imputed to us, all which the Scripture ſpeaks of this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt in the Text. I conclude there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it not being the Eſſential Righteouſneſs of Chriſt as God, it is his Mediatorial Righteouſneſs, that Righteouſneſs which Chriſt as Mediator, and by Virtue of his being clothed with that Office, doth bring in before God for us.</p>
            <p>Propoſition III. <hi>It is that part of Chriſts Mediatorial Righteouſneſs which belongs to his Prieſtly Office, and is brought in by him as a Prieſt.</hi> Chriſt is Righteous as a Prophet, and as a King, and that for us, that is, for our good and benefit: But this Righteouſneſs of his in the Adminiſtration of theſe his Offices, is not the Righteouſneſs here ſpoken of; for it is not unto and upon Believers, that is, it is not imputed to them, nor is it upon them through Faith. Chriſt admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters his Prophetical Office righteouſly, namely according to the Law thereof, the command given him by his Father. He diſcovers to us what he hath ſeen with, and received of his Father for that end. So he did when on Earth,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94055:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.18. and 3, 32, 34. and 5.19. and 8.38. and 12.49, 50. And now he is in Heaven, he goes by the ſame rule in revealing his Fathers Counſels to us, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1. Both in Heaven and on Earth he <hi>ſpeaks in righteouſneſs, Iſa.</hi> 63.1. Chriſt doth adminiſter his Kingly-Office in Righteouſneſs; he gives Righteous Laws and Ordinances, and Executes Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgments, and Adminiſters all the Affairs of the World, and of his Church moſt Righteouſly, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.1. He is <hi>a King that reigns in righteouſneſs; Pſal.</hi> 145.17. <hi>All his ways are holy, and all his judgments juſt. Rev.</hi> 15.3. and 16.5, 7. The Judgments which he executeth on his Enemies, and for his People, are Holy and Juſt, and he is True and Righteous in executing of them. But this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt in his Adminiſtring his Prophetical and Kingly Offices is not the Righteouſneſs which here in the Text is ſaid to be upon us. For in his Prophetical and Kingly Adminiſtration he acts <hi>from God towards us,</hi> but in bringing in this Righteouſneſs which is upon us, through Faith, and wherein we ſtand ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, he acts <hi>towards God for us,</hi> which is the proper work of his Prieſtly-Office, as the Apoſtle expreſly declares and aſſerts. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.1. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.3.</p>
            <p>Some there are who ſay, That the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt which is upon us through Faith is his Mediatorial Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; but either they therein do mean the Righteouſneſs which as a Prieſt he brings in before God for us, or it is too wide an Expreſſion: None that I know of but <hi>Socinians</hi> or <hi>Semiſocinians</hi> (who do really deny the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs to us, though they ſeem in words ſometimes to own it) do ſpeak of the Imputation to us, of any part of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt's Adminiſtring his Prophetical or Kingly Offices.</p>
            <p>For the ſame reaſon for which I limit this Righteouſneſs which is upon us through Faith to the Righteouſneſs brought in by Chriſt as a Prieſt, I conceive the Incarnation of Chriſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94055:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>(taken preciſely as abſtracted from the Condition that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it all the days of his frailty is not a part of this Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs. If any will needs call it a part of this Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, inaſmuch as he therein did according to the Will of his Father, and according to his own undertaking, I would not much contend with them, though the Expreſſion be both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accurate and inſnaring. But I can by no means grant it to be a part of this Righteouſneſs. For it is no part of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation of Chriſt, or of his Satisfaction, or of his Obedience to the precept of the Moral Law; not of his Humiliation, (by his Humiliation, I mean that Abaſed State of Chriſt which is contradiſtinguiſh'd and oppoſed to his Exaltation) for his Humiliation was of the Whole Perſon in both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the ground of it was our Sins being upon him as our Surety, and ally'd in Blood to us, and all the while he was in a State of Humiliation he was under the Curſe. But certainly Chriſt is not now under the Curſe, and yet he doth now dwell in our Nature in his State of Exaltation: Nor is Chriſt's Incarnation a part of his Satisfaction: For Satisfaction, to ſpeak properly, is made to the Juſtice of God, and the Demands thereof, by Vertue of the Moral Law, and not meerly to the Juſt and Righteous Will of God the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver. Satisfaction is a repaying and making amends for Wrong done, and not barely a pleaſing of the Will and Mind of him to whom Satisfaction is made, and thence Satisfaction is the Fruit and Effect of Puniſhment. But Chriſts dwelling in our Nature is no part of the Puniſhment of Sin, for then the Divine Nature only is puniſhed, and not the Humane at all, nor the Perſon. Beſides, it may as juſtly be ſaid to be a part of his Exaltation as of his Humiliation; for the Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſubſiſting in Perſonal Union with the Divine, hath an higher and better ſubſiſtence then any it could have had in ſubſiſting by it ſelf. Nor Laſtly, Is it a part of his Obedience to the Precept of the Moral Law: For the Law took not hold
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94055:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon him, he was not under it before his Incarnation, and therefore could not be bound by it to become Incarnate. For theſe and ſuch like reaſons, Divines of very Subact and Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Judgments have denyed the Aſſumption of the Humane Nature to be any part of the Satisfaction or Humiliation of Chriſt. So <hi>Bradſhaw of Juſtif. ch.</hi> 17. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. and <hi>Ames Med. Theol. l.</hi> 1.<hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>And I do the rather note it, and deſire it may be obſerv'd and taken in by you, becauſe ſome who have lookt upon Chriſt Incarnation as a part of his Humiliation, have alſo deny'd any other manner of Imputation of his Righteouſneſs than what agrees to, and may be affirmed of his Incarnation; Namely, that it is for our behoof and benefit, and that the Effects and Fruits of it are communicated to us, but his Righteouſneſs it ſelf is not upon us according to them, and is not imputed to us at all. I will iſſue this point thus, which alſo further clears it up. There is a difference in the Nature of the things, and diſtinction therefore to be made in our thoughts, between the Incarnation of Chriſt, and the Condition or Form of a Servant, in which he did come and appear in our Fleſh from the firſt moment of his aſſuming it until he enter'd on his eſtate of his Exaltation. The aſſuming of our Nature was an Act of Love and Grace to us ward, and great Condeſcenſion in the Son of God, and it belongs to the Conſtitution of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as he now is, and is one thing wherein conſiſts his Fitneſs for that work of Mediation, to which he was called, and which he had undertaken; But his ſubjection to the Law, and his fulfilling it in the <hi>form of a Servant</hi> is that Righteouſneſs brought in by him for us, which is upon us through Faith.</p>
            <p>Propoſition IV. <hi>Among the performances of Chriſt as a Prieſt, this Righteouſneſs is his Sponſory, Fide-juſſory, or Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhip Righteouſneſs,</hi> viz. <hi>That Righ eouſneſs, which as our Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he was obliged to bring in for us, and did ſo.</hi> I do thus bring
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94055:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>down and confine this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt which is upon us, unto his Suretiſhip-righteouſneſs, (which is ſomewhat narrower than the whole of Chriſts perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances as a Prieſt) becauſe there are ſome things which Chriſt did as a Prieſt, which yet cannot be ſaid to be any part of this righteouſneſs which is upon us. As for inſtance, Chriſt paſſed through all thoſe viſible lower Heavens, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.14. and aſcended far above them all, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10. and this he did as a Prieſt, (though not only as a Prieſt) for it was prefigured and foretold by the Prieſts going daily from the Altar of Braſs which ſtood without the Temple, up unto the Altar of Gold for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, which ſtood within the Sanctuary before the Vayl, and by the High Prieſts going once a year in the great day of Atonement, up from the Brazen Altar before the door with the Blood of his Sacrifice, and with Incenſe alſo into the Holy of Holies unto the Mercy-Seat. But Chriſt Aſcenſion or going to Heaven is not a part of this righteouſneſs, nor upon us through Faith, as this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is.</p>
            <p>Again, (to give another inſtance) Chriſt doth <hi>intercede,</hi> and in his ſo doing he fulfils the Law of his Prieſtly Office; For it was Typified by the Prieſts offering up Incenſe, and by his bearing the Names of the Twelve Tribes on his Shoulders, and on his Breaſt-plate. But the Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt cannot be ſaid to be any part of this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which is here ſaid to be upon us. Though it be of precious and effectual avail for us, and doth procure all our ſaying Mercies, yet it is not imputed to us, it is no part of his <hi>Suretiſhip-Righteouſneſs</hi> which he hath brought in for us before God.</p>
            <p>Propoſition V. <hi>This Suretiſhip-Righteouſneſs of Chriſt which is through Faith upon Believers, is his perfect Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94055:8"/>to the Moral Law in all that which the Juſtice of God did by virtue thereof demand in behalf of the Elect from Chriſt as their Surety; that they might not onely in a way of Grace, but in a way of Juſtice, be brought to that Eternal Bleſſedneſs and Glory whereto God in his infinite love had appointed them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ground of Chriſts bringing in this righteouſneſs, is his being our <hi>Surety:</hi> So he is made by God the Father, and by his own undertaking; in that Covenant between God and him was he conſtituted a <hi>Surety.</hi> So he is called expreſly, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.22. and the thing wherein <hi>Suretiſhip</hi> doth conſiſt, is abundantly affirmed of him in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Some indeed who would not be accounted <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> wrangle againſt and reject this Counſel of God againſt themſelves, and thence would have it underſtood either metaphorically, <hi>So Trum. gr. propit. pag.</hi> 88, 100. or of his being <hi>Gods Surety to us,</hi> to aſſure to us his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of his Promiſes, <hi>See Mr.</hi> B. <hi>Script. Goſp. def. p.</hi> 76, 78. But the thing is plain. He who is obliged to pay anothers Debt, or any part of it, is properly and in ſtrictneſs his Surety. Now ſo it is between Chriſt and us, he was obliged to pay our Debt, and hath done it accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. His name was put in, into the original bond, in which we by the Law and Covenant of our creation were bound. Herein as God hath in his Infinite Love and Grace conſulted well for us, ſo he hath acted according to his own bleſſed Supremacy, and adorable Wiſdom, without any the leaſt impeachment of his. Juſtice or his Truth in his Law. For though the Law name onely us, and do directly, firſtly and immediately bind us as the principal Debtors, yet God in ſubſtituting his Son to be our Surety, doth not in the leaſt recede from his own Truth, or from the equity and juſtice of the Law. For as in Contracts between man and man, the end and intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94055:8"/>is that the debt be paid, whether by the original Debtor himſelf who contracted it, or by another for him, it is all one as to the rights of the Creditor, they are juſtly preſerved and provided for either way. So it is here. The higheſt end and main intendment of the Law is the preſerving and ſecuring unto God the honour of his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, Wiſdom, Holineſs and Juſtice. And this is not departed from but provided for and purſued (and that with much advantage unto Gods glory as well as our good) in his conſtituting Chriſt our Surety. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Gods calling Chriſt unto the work of bringing in this righteouſneſs for us, he doth neither revoke nor make void the Law, nor recede from his own immutable Truth and Holineſs ſhining in it, but eſtabliſheth it, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle declares, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25, 26, 31.</p>
            <p>The rule of this righteouſneſs, by which it is meaſured, is the Moral Law, and the demands of the Juſtice of God in our behalf according to it: Hence, God by this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt doth <hi>magnifie his Law and make it Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ourable,</hi> as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.21. When I ſay the <hi>Moral Law</hi> is the rule of this righteouſneſs of Chriſt, I would not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as excluding his obſerving the <hi>Ceremonial Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> from being a part of his Righteouſneſs. It is of Moral Obligation that the poſitive Ordinances of God ſhould be obſerved, and Chriſt himſelf ſpeaks of his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving that poſitive Ordinance of Baptiſm, as a thing that was incumbent on him, that he might fulfill all righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.15.</p>
            <p>The end of this Suretiſhip-righteouſneſs of Chriſt is, with reference to us, that we might; and its attainment is that we muſt and ſhall be brought in a way wherein Juſtice as well as Grace is glorified unto that bleſſedneſs to which God in his Infinite Love hath fore-appointed us. Hence it appears that Electing Love is not the effect or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94055:9"/>fruit of this righteouſneſs, but is indeed the cauſe and ſpring of it, Election is not procured by it, but the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of this righteouſneſs for us is ordained by the Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love of God to us. So the Scripture ſpeaks <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. and 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.9, 10.</p>
            <p>God in his Electing us, appointed us unto an higher bliſs and glory than was propoſed to the <hi>firſt Adam</hi> in his Covenant, or than he could ever have brought his Seed unto. He was of the <hi>Earth Earthly, Chriſt is the Lord from Heaven,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. and the Elect are appointed to be married to the Son of God, made members of him, and co-heirs with him, and to be Sons of God, as in Chriſt their Head, to whom they are predeſtinated to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in their Dignities and Priviledges, as well as in their qualities, ſpiritual Principles, and the frame of their Hearts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. They are to judge the World, yea, to judge Angels at the great day, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2, 3. and in the mean time while they are here they are to be ſerved and miniſtred unto by them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. And at laſt there will be a day when the love wherewith the Father hath loved Chriſt ſhall appear to be in them, and Chriſt in them, and the World ſhall know that the Father hath loved them as he hath loved Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.23, 26. Theſe are things higher than <hi>Adam</hi> or his Covenant would have brought them unto. Yet unto theſe things muſt they be brought in a way wherein not onely Grace but Juſtice alſo ſhall ſhine forth and be glorified. And therefore God in ſetting a Crown of Glory on their heads exerts his Juſtice as well as his Grace, his righteouſneſs as well as his Mercy, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. it is a <hi>Crown of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> given by the Lord the <hi>righteous judge.</hi> And as in our being glorified, the righteouſneſs of God is exerted and ſhineth forth, ſo it is likewiſe in our being juſtified, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25, 26. and indeed throughout the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94055:9"/>whole of our Salvation, <hi>he is a juſt God and a Saviour, Iſa.</hi> 45.21.</p>
            <p>Hence appears the Neceſſity of this Suretiſhip-Righteouſneſs of Chriſt. It muſt be provided and brought in that God may be Juſt in ſhowing Mercy, and appear Righteous in extending Grace unto us, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us with that great Salvation, to which he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed us. For it is the unchangeable Conſtitution of the unchangeable God, to glorifie the one Attribute as well as the other, Juſtice as well as Grace in our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>Of this Suretiſhip-Righteouſneſs of Chriſt there are two parts, without either of which, it would not be compleat and perfect, and would not ſerve our turn: And the reaſon thereof is, becauſe Chriſt being our Surety, is thereby under an Obligation to pay our Debt, and we owe a double Debt unto the Moral Law; <hi>viz.</hi> a Debt of Satisfaction, by ſuffering the penalty, as tranſgreſſing guilty Creatures, and a Debt of Service and Obedience to the Precept as rational Creatures conſtituted in the way to our Everlaſting Condition. Hence there are two parts of Chriſt's Suretiſhip-righteouſneſs. This is that which the Apoſtle ſaith, and on which he puts ſo much Remark and Emphaſis, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.6. <hi>This is he who came by water and by blood, Jeſus the Chriſt, not</hi> in <hi>water only, but in water</hi> and <hi>in blood.</hi> The Language and Phraſes are Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical: Conceive the meaning of them thus. The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> came by Water, in a Spotleſs Cleanneſs, and Purity, as to all that the Precept requir'd of him: But Jeſus Chriſt came not by Water only, not only in ſuch Purity and Cleanneſs as fully anſwered all the Demands of the Precept of the Law; but he came by Blood alſo, (which neither <hi>Adam</hi> nor Angels did) Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God came in a way of ſatisfactory Sufferings to Expiate and make
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94055:10"/>Atonement for the Sins againſt the Precept which we were guilty of; this he did by his Blood. The reaſon is, he was made our Surety, his Name was put not only into the Covenant of Works, but into it as a broken Covenant.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>His ſubjection to and ſuffering of the penalty of the Law.</hi> This is commonly called the <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> or Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt, becauſe it conſiſts in his Suffering the penalty or curſe of the Law. The Scripture calls it the Blood of Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. and the Death of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. under that eminent part including and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the whole of his Sufferings. And alſo Chriſt's being made Sin. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. and being made a Curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</p>
            <p>The ground and reaſon of this Suffering of Chriſt under the Curſe of the Law is becauſe our Guilt, our Sins were upon him, and thence he ſuffered in our ſtead for them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5, 6. God the Father with his own conſent put upon him the Garments of us Sinners, and then awaked his Sword againſt him, even the Sword of his Revenging Juſtice, and ran him through, and poured out his Blood as if he had been a Sinner, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.7.</p>
            <p>The end of it with reference to God is the reſtoring to him the Honour of his Authority and Supremacy over us, and of his other perfections which ſhine forth in the Law, which we by diſobeying him had robbed him of, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.4. With reference to us, the end and attainment of it is reconciling us to God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. Thence Chriſt is ſaid to reconcile us, and make peace between God and us by the blood of his Croſs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.14, 15, 16. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.20, 21.</p>
            <p>The neceſſity of this part of Chriſt's Suretiſhip-righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs being brought in for us, ariſeth partly from the glorious Holineſs and Juſtice of Gods Nature, whence he cannot but maintain his own Supremacy, and the Rational Creatures Moral dependance on, and ſubjection to himſelf;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94055:10"/>which being violated by Sin, can no way be re by ſatisfaction, nor ſatisfaction be made, but by the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Puniſhment; and partly from the veracity of God in his threatning, wherein he hath in Wiſdom and Juſtice eſtabliſhed a connexion between Sin and Death, and made the latter to be the wages of the former, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26. Inſomuch as in regard of the Sanction of the Law, that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb,</hi> 9.22. takes place, and holds true, <hi>without blood there is no remiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>His ſubjection to, and fulfilling the precept of the Law</hi> is alſo a part of Chriſt's Suretiſhip-Righteouſneſs. This is commonly called Chriſt's <hi>active obedience,</hi> and by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle his Obedience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. <hi>viz.</hi> Obedience not only in Suffering, but Obedience to the precept of the Law; as <hi>Adams</hi> Diſobedience, to which it is there oppoſed was a violation of the precept. By Chriſt it is called his fulfilling all righteouſneſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.15. and his doing the will of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.8. Heb. 10.7, 9.</p>
            <p>The reaſon and ground of Chriſts obligation to bring in this part of righteouſneſs for us, is, becauſe he is our Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and we owe this Debt to the Law of God.</p>
            <p>And there is a neceſſity of it, becauſe God will magnifie his Law, and make it Honourable in his being well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Chriſt with us for his righteouſneſs ſake, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.21 And becauſe it is the unchangeable conſtitution of God that all the ſaying Good and Bleſſing which ſhall be given us, ſhall be given not only from Free Grace, but by the hand of Juſtice, and in the way of being purchaſed for us by a juſt price. Thence, as in the former part of Chriſt's Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhip-righteouſneſs, God's vindictive juſtice appeared and was glorified, ſo in this part of it his remunerative juſtice ſhines forth and is exerted. For by this part of Chriſt's righteouſneſs he hath obtained for us in a way of purchaſe or merit, by paying down a juſt price, Salvation and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.14.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:94055:11"/>
            <p>Under this Obedience or Conformity of Chriſt to the Precept of the Law, I include both all the courſe of his Holy walking, and alſo the habitual created inherent Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of his humane Nature; for the precept of the Law requires Holineſs both in heart and Life, and therefore Chriſt paid both, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.26, 28. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.9. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22. and 3.18.</p>
            <p>I mention this in the ſecond place after the other part of his Suretiſhip-righteouſneſs, becauſe though that was compleated and finiſhed at his Death; and his Active Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the precept of the Moral Law was yielded in his Life, yet the conſideration of them, and the Natural order of them as availing and accepted for us, is, that ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the penalty goes before Obedience to the precept, becauſe there is no room for merit or purchaſe till ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be firſt made. As among Men you cannot purchaſe of another till your Debt be paid and former Arrearages, into which you have run with him, be ſatisfied and cleared.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs you muſt not ſo underſtand this, as if theſe two parts of this Suretiſhip-righteouſneſs of Chriſt were brought in at ſeveral times, and did not co-exiſt together: For they did concur and meet in many, if not in all the paſſages of his Life in the Fleſh, during the whole courſe thereof. For though his Incarnation be not any part of this his Suretiſhip-righteouſneſs as you heard, yet the form of a Servant, or that abaſed Condition wherein he was from the firſt moment of his Conception, and wherein he acted all along his Life, is a part of his Humiliation. And on the other hand there was Active Obedience in his Death and Sufferings, becauſe his own Will was in it: For he offered up himſelf, and he laid down his own Life, and this in obedience to the command which he had received from his Father, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.17, 18. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.31. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.4.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:94055:11"/>
            <p>Thus I have gone through the firſt thing propoſed to be ſpoken to, namely, <hi>what this righteouſneſs of God is,</hi> which is through Faith upon all that believe, and you have ſeen that,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is the righteouſneſs of Chriſt.</hi> 2. <hi>It is his Mediato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial righteouſneſs.</hi> 3. <hi>It is the righteouſneſs which is brought in by him as a Prieſt.</hi> 4. <hi>It is hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Suretiſhip-righteouſneſs.</hi> 5. <hi>This Suretiſhip righteouſneſs of Chriſt is his perfect an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering in behalf of the Elect as our Surety all the demands of the juſtice of God by vertue of the Moral Law, that they might, in a way of juſtice as well as grace be brought unto that happineſs whereto they are appointed, and it contains both his bearing the Penalty, and his fulfilling the Precept of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now proceed to the remaining Enquiries, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſhall be briefer.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>How is this Righteouſneſs unto and upon thoſe that believe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As to theſe words <hi>unto</hi> and <hi>upon</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there is ſomewhat a divers account given of them. Some conceive they are here uſed by the Apoſtle in a different ſenſe; as if the firſt referred to the deſignment, the ſecond to the actual Donation of this Righteouſneſs, or as if the one were uſed and meant of the tender and promiſe, the other of the actual giving and transferring of this Righteouſneſs to and on Believers. Others conceive the ſenſe and intendment of them both is much what one and the ſame in this Text. as it is of <hi>by</hi> and <hi>through v.</hi> 30 and conſequently that the Apoſtle here uſeth both theſe words that he may more fully and emphatically expreſs our Intereſt in, and Benefit by this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt. And I confeſs I doe rather incline to this latter account of theſe two Prepoſitions, the reaſons whereof I need not now to inſiſt on; but ſhall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to declare how this Righteouſneſs is <hi>unto</hi> and <hi>upon</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94055:12"/>and I ſhall expreſs it in four words only noting firſt that that being upon us of this Righteouſneſs which the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of, is unto Juſtification of Life; as appears from the whole Context: See <hi>ver.</hi> 20. and <hi>ver.</hi> 24. and <hi>ver.</hi> 28. and <hi>ver.</hi> 30.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>This righteouſneſs it ſelf is upon Believers by the free and gracious gift and imputation of God.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt uſeth both theſe expreſſions in this matter. You read of the gift of Righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17. and of the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6,11. With reſpect to us it is wholly free and gracious, for thoſe to whom it is given and imputed do no more deſerve it than thoſe who never ſhall be intereſted in it: Though with reſpect to Chriſt it is juſt and equal that it ſhould be imputed to us; in as much as he did bring it in for us, and that under an Expectation and Aſſurance built upon God the Fathers Covenant with him, that it ſhould be accepted, and of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail for us, and given and reckoned to us. By being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, I mean that it is looked on by God as belonging to us, in order to our being judicially dealt withal according to the merit thereof. This is the Notion of Imputation in the general, be the thing imputed good or evil, be it originally our own or anothers. And hence it appears that it is this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt it ſelf, which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, and not only the Effects or Benefits of it which are procured by it communicated to us; for this is in truth no Imputation. It cannot be ſaid in any Congruity or Truth either that Juſtification and Adoption are imputed to us, or that the Interceſſion of Chriſt in Heaven is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us. Yet the former are communicated to us through the imputation of this Righteouſneſs, and of the latter we do receive the benefit. None that I know of ever ſaid that the Reſurrection and Aſcenſion of Chriſt are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94055:12"/>imputed to us; yet are we made partakers of the Effects and benefits of them. To deny that Chriſt's Suretiſhip-Righteouſneſs it ſelf is imputed to us, is to fall in with the <hi>Socinians,</hi> and the very thing which they contend for. And indeed the thing is plain, that in our being juſtified, either this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt it ſelf, or a Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our own muſt be imputed to us. For there cannot be Juſtification without the Imputation of a Righteouſneſs, any more than there can be Condemnation without the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of a Crime; and beſides, the Scripture ſpeaks ſo much of Imputation in the Buſineſs of Juſtification, that I know not any who would be called Chriſtians that have denyed all Imputation in that matter. And thence it is, that thoſe, who have either out of Darkneſs, or out of Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt ſtanding in the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt denyed the Imputation of that very Righteouſneſs it ſelf unto us, have all of them ſubſtituted another Righteouſneſs, even a Righteouſneſs of our own for us to ſtand in before God, and be juſtified in.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>This gratious Imputation is valid and effectual to conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Believers righteous.</hi> So the Apoſtle tells us moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. <hi>As by one mans diſobedience many were made Sinners, ſo by the obedience of one ſhall many be made righteous.</hi> The word which the Apoſtle there uſeth, and is rendred <hi>made,</hi> ſignifies conſtituted, and points to Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as the way how we are made Righteous. And beſides, he tells us it is in the ſame manner, <hi>as</hi> we are conſtituted Sinners by <hi>Adams</hi> diſobedience, <hi>ſo</hi> in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we were made Righteous by Chriſt's Obedience. But the former, namely our being made Sinners is by the Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to us of <hi>Adam</hi>'s diſobedience, by it Judgment was, or Criminalneſs came upon all Men to Condemnation, as <hi>ver.</hi> 16. and <hi>ver.</hi> 18. and therefore by the free gift and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94055:13"/>Imputation of this Righteouſneſs of the Second <hi>Adam</hi> doth Juſtification, even Juſtification unto life come upon us. Such a validity and efficacy there in is Gods Gift and Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that by this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt it being impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them, Believers have a Title and Right to pardon, to the Favour of God, to Adoption, and to Eternal Life. On account of this Righteouſneſs being thus made theirs, it is, as I conceive, that they are ſaid to be <hi>Worthy, Rev.</hi> 3.4. to walk with Chriſt in white; worthy of Joyful Communion with Chriſt, not in themſelves, but as in him, and having his Righteouſneſs upon them, in whom they are made the Righteouſneſs of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>This Righteouſneſs is upon Believers not only for the change of their Eſtate at firſt from a State of Wrath and Condemnation, to a State of Favour with God and Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but alſo for the continuing of them in that Eſtate for ever.</hi> This is that which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.21. Grace reigneth through Righteouſneſs unto Eternal Life. So that Believers ſtand before God in this Righteouſneſs, having it upon them all their Life, as well as at their firſt belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and being tranſlated into a juſtified Eſtate. It is in this Righteouſneſs in which they ſtand juſtified, and not in their own Graces of Sanctification, or in any of their own new obedience. Thus the Holy Ghoſt teacheth us to judge and believe when he ſaith, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.12 <hi>If any man ſin,</hi> (that is, if any Believer ſin, for of them he ſpeaks) <hi>we have an Advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous, and he is,</hi> no only was or hath been, but <hi>he is a propitiation for our ſins.</hi> And 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 1.7. <hi>If we walk in the light as God is in the light, the blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us from all Sin.</hi> Our walking in the Light hath no influence at all to cleanſe us from the filth contracted by the leaſt Sin that is found with us. This I take to be one
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94055:13"/>reaſon why it is called <hi>Everlaſting Righteouſneſs, Dan.</hi> 9.24 The Righteouſneſs of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> in which he was created was not ſo, no, he ſinn'd and forfeited, and loſt it, it laſted no longer than while he continued in all things contained in the Law to do them. But it is not ſo with the Righteouſneſs which the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> brings in, if it be once upon us through Faith, it is upon us everlaſtingly. Thence Believers are ſaid to be <hi>b fore the Throne of God without fault. Rev.</hi> 14.5. which is much too high an expreſſion to be uſed of the beſt Saint under Heaven on the account of his Obedient and Holy Walking; nothing but the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt being upon them can ſet them before the Throne of God without fault. Of this mind was the Holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> when with ſo much vehemency and pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticalneſs he renounceth his own Righteouſneſs, and ſhuns ſtanding in it for Juſtification unto Life, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. as <hi>droſs</hi> that was of no wortlh, as <hi>loſs</hi> that would undoe him, yea, as <hi>dung</hi> which would defile him, and render him abhorred. This he ſpeaks of his own Righteouſneſs, and thus his heart ſtood affected towards it in the buſineſs of his Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, even then when he had been converted and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified many years, and done and ſuffered much for Chriſt in an excellent manner, and with a choice and Evangelical Spirit. <hi>Bellarmin</hi> indeed would have <hi>Paul</hi> there by his own Righteouſneſs, to mean nothing but his own Hypocriſie or formality, and is ſo very angry with <hi>Chemnitius</hi> for inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>own Righteouſneſs</hi> there, and the <hi>[all things]</hi> which he renounceth as comprizing them under his Grace of Sanctification, and his new Obedience, that he chargeth him for it with blaſphemy. And indeed 'tis no wonder, if depreciating and crying down a Mans own Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs be reſented as Blaſphemy by a proud Cardinal, an haughty Jeſuit and blind Papiſt. But the Light and Pregnancy of the Apoſtles Expreſſions are ſo ſtrong and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94055:14"/>clear, that it is ſomewhat ſurprizing, that any pretending to be a Proteſtant

<note n="(a)" place="margin">Such as Dr. <hi>Sherl.</hi> See <hi>Antiſoz. p. 547</hi> to <hi>568,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Williams.</hi> See <hi>Pref. p. 9.</hi> and <hi>p. 202, 203, 204, 209. Grotius</hi> indeed goes the ſame way. <hi>Annot.</hi> in <hi>loc.</hi> And I learn by Mr. <hi>Rutherf.</hi> of the <hi>Cov. p. 171.</hi> that <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians</hi> and <hi>Socinians</hi> do ſo too. But I do not reckon him or them among Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. It is like <hi>Grotius</hi> and the <hi>Arminians</hi> might have it from the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covian Catechiſme, cap. 9. p. 194.</hi>
               </note>

ſhould lick up that Popiſh Self-juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaries vomit. But vain Man would be wiſe, though he be born like the wild Aſſes Colt. There is in us an obſtinate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herency to our own Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and a deſperate loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to foregoe it, and be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten off utterly from it. And thence, if we ſee we cannot have any thing of our own before Converſion to bring us into a juſtified State, yet we ſtruggle as for Life, that ſomewhat of our own, ſomething done by us, or inhering in us, may ſome way or other be our Juſtifying Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, or a part of it, may have ſome band in continuing us in that Eſtate, though it could do nothing to bring us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. But doubtleſs Holy <hi>David</hi>'s heart was under the conduct of the Bleſſed Spirit of Wiſdom and Grace, when he reſolved to <hi>make mention of the Righteouſneſs of God, and of it only,</hi> for his acceptance, as well as to <hi>walk in the ſtrength of the Lord God,</hi> for his Aſſiſtance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.16. And this was not at firſt. Converſion only that he might be put into a State of Juſtification, but it was when he was old and gray-headed, and had been ſanctified and done much for God, and been in a juſtified Eſtate many Years. See <hi>ver.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>This free, effectual, valid, abiding imputation of this righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs unto Believers is ſuch, and it is through Faith ſo upon them, that they are thereby conſtituted as righteous as Chriſt is righteous as their Surety.</hi> When I ſay they are by its being upon them made as Righteous as Chriſt is Righteous, as he is their Surety, I mean it not in a way of Similitude only,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94055:14"/>but in a way of Equality. I am well aware that this is looked on as a monſtrous abſurdity and horrid impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity by <hi>Papiſts</hi> and others, who contend againſt the Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt unto us at all And no wonder, for Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs are <hi>a ſtumbling ſtone and rock of offence to many in Iſrael;</hi> it was ſo of old, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.32, 33. and it will be to as long as that word, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. ſtands firm, that there are any in the World who are appointed to ſtumble at that ſtumbling ſtone. But we muſt not foregoe a truth ſo certain, ſo clear, ſo comfortable, though all the Unbelievers in the World ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and quarrel at it. That I may, if poſſible, prevent the offence, I deſire you would obſerve that I do not make compariſon between the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and the Righteouſneſs of Believers, by their being ſanctified, and their Holy walking. In this regard there is only a ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, to dream of an Equality, would be prodigious Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and blaſphemous Madneſs. Nor is the compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon between the Righteouſneſs of Believers by Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and their Righteouſneſs in point of Sanctification. Theſe are not the things compared together. To make theſe equal would be fooliſh in it ſelf, and uncomfortable for Believers: For alas the Righteouſneſs of the Holyeſt Believer, if we ſpeak of his Sanctification and Holy walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is far from being perfect. But the compariſon is between the effect of this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt upon him as their Surety, and the effect of the ſame Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt upon Believers, as it is made theirs by the Gift and Imputation of God. And moreover, what other or further effect it may have upon Chriſt I now conſider not, but limit the compariſon on that ſide to the effect it hath upon him as their Surety in making him Righteous. And thus underſtood it is a clear and certain Truth that believers by the Imputation of it to them are as righteous
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94055:15"/>as Chriſt is Righteous as their Surety. For as he is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Righteous, having fully paid their Debt, and being fully diſcharged, ſo are they in him. There is no condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to them no, not one, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. Their ſins though in themſelves as Scarlet, red as Crimſon, are yet made as Snow and white as Wool. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.18. Their Iniquities though ſought for, yet are as if they were not, and though ſearched for, yet ſhall not be found: So perfect and full is Gods pardon, ſo complete is God's juſtifying of them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.20. There is none can condemn them, there is none can lay any thing to the charge of thoſe Elect of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33, 34. They do ſtand before the Throne of God without fault, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.5. For they are made the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. then which no higher, no more full or emphatical Expreſſions are any where uſed of Chriſt's being righteous as their Surety, nor can be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily invented. Moreover thoſe very words which the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt uſeth by the Prophet with reference to Chriſt's acquittal and righteouſneſs, as the Surety of Believers, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.7, 8, 9. <hi>viz.</hi> that he ſhall not be <hi>confounded,</hi> that he ſhall not be <hi>aſhmed,</hi> that he is <hi>juſtified;</hi> that there is none that ſhall <hi>condemn</hi> him; theſe very words doth the ſame Spirit by the Apoſtle uſe, and that in the ſame ſenſe concerning the diſcharge and righteouſneſs of Believers, through this righteouſneſs of Chriſts being upon them, namely, that they ſhall not be <hi>aſhamed,</hi> and that they ſhall <hi>not be confounded,</hi> that they are <hi>juſtified,</hi> and that there is none that ſhall <hi>condemn</hi> them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 33, 34. Thus ſhowing that this Suretiſhip-righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt which is through Faith upon all who believe hath as to this the very ſame effect upon them that it hath upon Chriſt as their Surety. And indeed the thing is ſo obvious and plain, that the Original Debter is as clear and free as his Surety is, considered as his Surety, when the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94055:15"/>Debt is paid and that Payment accepted for, and adjudged to the Original Debtor by the Creditor; that I ſee not what can poſſibly cauſe any to doubt of Believers being as righteous as Chriſt, is conſider'd as their Surety, if he be not influenced by a ſecret diſbelief of our being conſtituted Righteous by this Suretiſhip-Righteouſneſs of Chriſt being upon us, and imputed to us through Faith, or by a lothneſs at heart to ſtand juſtified in it only, and a deſire to ſtand righteous in ſome righteouſneſs or other of his own. And it is but too manifeſt that this lyes at the bottom with many who exclaim againſt it as an impoſſible thing, and a monſtrous paradox.</p>
            <p>Nor is it a truth only that Believers are in the ſenſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore given as righteous as Chriſt: But it is alſo true (and I the rather mention it, becauſe it tends to clear this whole matter) that Believers have that very ſame title to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God here, and to Heaven and Glory hereafter that Chriſt hath as he is their Surety. 'Tis true Chriſt hath ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther title and right both to the Love of God, and unto Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Glory, <hi>viz.</hi> by the prerogative of his Birth (if I may ſo expreſs it,) I mean his Eternal Generation, as he is the only begotten Son of God. But though he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was rich, yet ſuch is his Grace, that for our ſakes he became poor; he conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (not to foregoe this his title but) for a time to foregoe the actual injoyment of the full fruit and benefit of it. He was contented to lay aſide his Glory for a time, and to dwell here below on Earth under the frowns and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God his Father, until he ſhould fully to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt farthing have paid our Debt: But then he was to be reſtored and raiſed up to the injoyment of his Fathers Love and Heavenly Glory in the vertue of that forementioned double right or title, <hi>viz.</hi> bothas the Son of God by Nature, and alſo as having diſcharged all the Debt of the Elect as their Surety; this latter being accumulated and ſuperinduced
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94055:16"/>upon the former, and therefore being not a Natural, but an Acquired Title. Now it is of this latter, this Acquired Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle that I ſpeak of when I ſay Believers have the ſame Title to the Love of God, and Heavenly Glory that Chriſt as their Surety hath. For this his Title lyes in his having perfectly pleated God in all the Demands of his Juſtice, by virtue of the Moral Law. And this very thing is a Believers Title alſo, this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt which anſwers all the Demands of the Juſtice of God by the Moral Law, is through Faith without difference unto them all, and upon them all who do believe. I know right precious Faith may poſſibly ſtagger at theſe things they are ſo great, and ſo aſtoniſhing; I know alſo the Devil, whoſe Eye is Evil towards us, becauſe God is ſo exceeding good, doth malign our taking of them in, and feeding on them. And thence he doth labour to foreſtall and ſhut up our Hearts againſt them, both by miſ-repreſenting them, and by loading them with horrid conſequences, ſuch as a ſpirit of any tenderneſs cannot but abominate. Whereas thoſe Bleſſed Truths neither have any ſuch frightful and deformed face, if ſet and viewed in a true Light, nor are there any falſe or evil conſequences that can be inferred from them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that if poſſible I may remove all ſtumbling blocks and rocks of offence, let me ſubjoyn theſe four things further, with reference to what I have been delivering.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Nevertheleſs, <hi>Believers cannot be ſaid to be in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects righteous as Chriſt is righteous.</hi> No, far be ſuch a thought from us. To entertain it would be damning and blaſphemous Ignorance and Arrogance in conjunction. To ſay nothing of that vaſt imparity and diſproportion that there is between the inherent righteouſneſs of Chriſt and of Believers, which may be fitly called the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Sanctification, nor of the great Inequality that is between the righteouſneſs of the walk or practice of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94055:16"/>Chriſt and of Believers, which I may call the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Obedience; for as to this I did even now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that thereis no more but a reſemblance or likeneſs, the beſt Believer falling wofully ſhort of his bleſſed Pattern: Even with reference to this Suretiſhip-righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and its being on Believers, they cannot with any truth or ſobriety be ſaid to be in all reſpects righteous as Chriſt is righteous as he is their Surety. For this very Suretiſhip-righteouſneſs of Chriſt is upon him, as the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Native ſubject and efficient of it; he wrought it out. But it is on Believers by derivation from Chriſt as they are in him. Hence, the Glory of bringing it in is his, even Chriſt's peculiar and wholly Due to him alone, they ſhare not at all with him therein; though they do through his Grace participate in the righteouſneſs thus brought in by Chriſt, and in the precious Effects and Fruits of it. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over as it is Chriſts and upon him, it is a Publick or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Righteouſneſs, for he is a publick or common Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon being a Surety for all the Elect; as performed by him, it was performed for them all, as accepted from him, it was accepted for them all. But now every Believer is made Righteous by it for himſelf only, it is upon him not as a Publick, but only as a Private Particular Single Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And therefore though Chriſt by this Righteouſneſs be the Saviour and the Redeemer of the Church, yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be inferr'd as both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Socinians</hi> impotently argue and calumniate, that if it be imputed to Believers, and they ſtand righteous in it, they are Saviours and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemers as well as Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Believers are nevertheleſs ſtill under obligation to obey the Law, and to walk in all Holy Converſation and Godlineſs, unto all well-pleaſing before God.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15, 16. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.10. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.1. They are bound not only to do all that the Law requires, but to do it in a way of ſubjection to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of God in the Law, and to put a reſpect of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94055:17"/>to his Command upon all that they doe, as well as a reſpect of Love and Thankfulneſs upon all their Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.17. Though withal it is true that Believers ought not to yield Obedience to the Law in a Legal man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Spirit, nor from Legal or Old-Covenant Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, nor unto Old-Covenant Ends. They ought not to obey in a ſervile manner with ſlaviſh fear ruling in their hearts, nay they may not fear being caſt out of Covenant and favour with God for every failure of theirs; Nor are they to obey only in the ſtrength of Grace received, but to depend on Chriſt for continual Influences as well as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant acceptance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.16. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.24. Nor laſtly may Believers obey the Law for the ſame end as under the Covenant of Works; namely, that their own Obedience ſhould be their righteouſneſs wherein to ſtand accepted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>All the ſwervings of Believers from the rule of the Law, and all their comings ſhort of what the precept doth require are ſins in them, notwithſtanding this righteouſneſs is thus upon them.</hi> Yea theſe ſins of theirs do deſerve Eternal Death, as juſtly, as much as the like ſins in others do. Nay they are worſe in Believers, being greatly aggravated, and of deeper demerit by this very thing, that the Grace of God hath thus appeared unto them, and hath thus exceedingly abounded to them-ward.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hence it follows further, That <hi>it is the Duty of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, notwithſtanding this righteouſneſs is upon them, and they are thus righteous by it, to lament their ſins, and to loath them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for them, yea to arraign and condemn themſelves as worthy of Eternal Death for even the leaſt of them.</hi> That promiſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.61, 63. holds out this to be a Duty and a Practiſe pleaſing unto God. Such alſo was the practice of that Converted pardoned Sinner, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.37, 38, 47. Her Sins were pardoned, and ſhe was juſtified before, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94055:17"/>not for or by her ſo lamenting and condemning her ſelf. This righteouſneſs therefore being thus upon Believers, ſhould not either incourage them unto Sin, or harden their hearts under ſin, neither indeed doth it, nor can it ſo work in a Believer. The abounding of Grace to them much more than Sin hath abounded, doth oblige and teach them to abhor continuing in Sin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.21. with <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1. Yea Believers ſhould argue with, and reprove them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for their Sins as <hi>Nathan</hi> from God argues with <hi>David</hi> about his Sin, and aggravates it upon him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.7, 8, 9. Even ſo ſhould Believers aggravate their own ſins upon themſelves, and load their own hearts with them from this Grace of God towards them, that this righteouſneſs of Chriſt is upon them: Therefore when I ſaid they ſhould arraign and condemn themſelves for their ſins, you muſt not underſtand it as if a Believer, upon whom this righteouſneſs of Chriſt is, ſhould judge himſelf to be in a ſtate of wrath: No, that would be a falſe Judgment, for there is no condemnation to thoſe who are in Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. But a Believer reflecting on his ſins ſhould lay his Mouth in the duſt, and his Neck down upon the block, his Conſcience ſhould make this Judgment, and paſs this Sentence on him, I am for ſuch and ſuch things which I have done againſt the Lord worthy of Eternal Death, yea I am more worthy of Hell than others, I do deſerve a deeper place in it than thoſe to whom Grace never ſo abounded, over whom Grace never ſo reigned through this righteouſneſs of Chriſt as it hath and will over me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>What is the import of that word</hi> without diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhall lay before you the intendment of it in three words.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94055:18"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>This righteouſneſs of God is upon all Believers,</hi> one as well as another, <hi>Gentile</hi> as well as <hi>Jew,</hi> greater as well as leſſer Sinners; even all who have ſinned and are fallen ſhort of the Glory of God, as <hi>ver.</hi> 23. all who are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come guilty before God, and whoſe mouths muſt be ſtopped, even all the World, as <hi>ver.</hi> 19. All fleſh who can never be juſtified in the ſight of God by the deeds of the Law; all who are in this common Condition of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind ſhall have this Righteouſneſs upon them, only provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they do believe. Nothing ſhall hinder, nothing in their outward Condition, nothing in their Spiritual Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall hinder the being upon them of this righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in caſe they do believe: That of the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. and <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.11. holds true, and takes place in this matter, that here there is neither <hi>Jew</hi> nor <hi>Greek,</hi> Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion nor Uncircumciſion, <hi>Barbarian, Scythian,</hi> Bond or Free, Male or Female; but this righteouſneſs is unto them all, and upon them all, one as well as another, if they believe. This Grace is extended to the greateſt, the fouleſt Sinners upon their believing, as well as unto the leaſt; according to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10, 11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>This righteouſneſs is equally and alike upon them all:</hi> There is in this alſo <hi>no difference,</hi> it is in the ſame meaſure and degree unto them all and upon them all. One hath not more of it than another; it is no leſs truely, no leſs certainly, no leſs validly and effectually given and imputed to one than it is unto another. 'Tis true indeed, there is a difference in the degree and meaſure wherein different Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are made partakers of ſome of the Effects and Fruits of this righteouſneſs; yea there is a difference as to this in the ſame Believer at different times. Sanctification and Comfort are the Effects of this righteouſneſs, and they are in different meaſures in different Believers, and in the ſame Believer at different times. But yet this righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94055:18"/>it ſelf is as much upon one Believer all Believers are equally juſtified or conſtituted righteous by it. They that have been the greateſt Sinners, and are moſt guilty, have it upon them through Faith, and are as well and as much made righteous by it as leſſer Sinners, one who hath done evil innumerable times, and whoſe days have been prolonged ſo that he is a ſinner of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years old, hath it upon him through Faith, and ſtands as righteous in it as an Infant of days doth. All that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve are alike, and equally juſtified; Goſpel-Juſtification admits not of any degrees that one ſhould be more or leſs juſtified than another, and therefore in this regard alſo there is no difference.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>This righteouſneſs is upon all that believe in the ſame way,</hi> viz. <hi>through Faith.</hi> No more, no other is required of one than of another, that this righteouſneſs may be upon him, namely, Faith, true Faith; though this true Faith may poſſibly be weaker in one, ſtronger in another. It is true indeed that on other accounts, and for other ends and from other grounds ſome things may be required of ſome which are not required of others. In ſome caſes Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in ſome caſes Confeſſion unto men even of ſecret Sins are required and inſiſted upon by God, <hi>Levit.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16. And in ſome Caſes deeper Humiliation and greater breakings of Heart than in others are called for and requiſite. But this is rather for the evidencing to a Mans own Conſcience or unto others the ſincerity and ſoundneſs of his own Faith and Repentance, and ſo the aſſuring of that, and clearing it up to them, or to a mans ſelf, then that this righteouſneſs of Chriſt may be upon him unto the Juſtification of Life. If a Man have true Faith, if he do truely believe, this righteouſneſs of Chriſt is upon him; though he be poſſibly both weak in Faith, and very defective in other graces of the Spirit, and in new
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94055:19"/>Obedience. Nay, all our New Obedience, and all the graces of the Spirit comprized under that one word <hi>love,</hi> are the effects and fruits of our being juſtified, having this Righteouſneſs upon us, and not at all the means thereof. It is a great and dangerous miſtake to think that either our New Obedience, or any other Grace but Faith hath any hand in this righteouſneſſes being upon us. No, it is through Faith, and Faith only.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> This Doctrine ſhows you, <hi>the reaſon and ſpring of that precious acceptance and ſweet communion with God which Believers are admitted into, and do injoy; and alſo of their humble rejoycings, and gloryings, and triumphings before God; notwithſtanding their guiltineſs and vileneſs in themſelves by their many and great ſinnings againſt him, and notwithſtanding their abaſing Convictions, and heart-wounding, heart-breaking ſenſe thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They have ſinned againſt God, they are guilty before him as well as others; for this is the Condition and State of all the World, <hi>Rom</hi> 3.19. Every Mouth is ſtopped and can have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſpeak againſt God when he judgeth and condemneth them, for all the World is become guilty. They are invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the common Guilt and Miſery and Ruine wherein all the Seed of <hi>Adam</hi> are plunged, and they have that excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſinful ſin dwelling in them which hath invaded all <hi>Adams</hi> poſterity: And moreover they have in their own Perſons ſinned againſt God, ſome of them more than many others: Yea they are all of them laid under Everlaſting Convictions of it in their own Conſciences which can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be blotted out, that they are worthy of Eternal Death. And ſome of them do with <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. walk up and down under ſuch Convictions, that they are amongſt the very chief of Sinners, and with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 86.13. That they have deſerved the very loweſt Hell.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:94055:19"/>
            <p>But yet nevertheleſs they have all of them precious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God, all their ſins are blotted out, God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members them no more for ever, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.12. Their treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes are done away as if they had never been, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.22. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.20. and they do ſtand without fault before the Throne of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.5. The reaſon of this wonderful abounding of Grace towards them is, this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is upon them.</p>
            <p>Nay they are not only pardoned and pronounced righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, notwithſtanding they have done ſo much and ſuch vile things againſt God, but they are alſo taken into ſpecial fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with him, they are made the Friends and Favourites of the God of Heaven, as their Father <hi>Abraham</hi> is ſtyled by <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.7. and by God himſelf, <hi>Ifa.</hi> 41.8. and all Believers by Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.14, 15. yea (which is ſomewhat higher) they are made Sons and Daughters unto the Lord God Almighty, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. <hi>Joh,</hi> 1.12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.10. Heirs of God and of Glory, Co-heirs with Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. Well may themſelves be raviſhed with admiration and ſweeteſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and call upon others to gaze and wonder at this love, (as the Apoſtle doth, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.1.) that ever they who were by Nature Heirs of Hell, and Children of Wrath and of the Devil, and who had by their ſinful, hateful do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings made themſelves manifold times more ſo, ſhould ever have ſuch love beſtowed upon them, as to be the Sons of God. But this gives the account of it, they are made thus highly accepted in that Beloved, whoſe righteouſneſs is upon them.</p>
            <p>Nor doth the Love and Favour of God reſt here in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving conferred ſuch Priviledges and Dignities upon them, but it goes on ſtill, (ſo mighty is the Torrent of Love which is let out upon them,) it doth bring them into a liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and near Communion with God, Father, Son, and Holy
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94055:20"/>Ghoſt, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13, 14. Though they were afar off, yet they are made nigh, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.13. and they have boldneſs and acceſs with confidence unto the Father, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.12. And God even the Father doth let out his heart-love, and manifeſt it and himſelf unto them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.21, 22, 23. Smiling upon their Souls, making them to go into his Houſe of Wine, and there in a victorious and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant manner, diſplaying over them his Love, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times even to an overwhelming, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.4, 5. Now if you ask whence is this, and how comes it to paſs that God deals with them in a way of ſuch marvellous Grace, this Doctrine tells you, the righteouſneſs of Chriſt is upon them.</p>
            <p>Moreover, The hearts of Believers are ſometimes raiſed up unto, and filled with enlarged rejoycings, humble glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and triumphings, and that before God. So the Apoſtle declares, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2, 3, 11. <hi>We rejoyce or glory in hope of the glory of God, and not only ſo, but we glory in tribulations alſo:</hi> And he comes over with that word again, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. ſaying, <hi>and not only ſo, but we glory in God;</hi> 'tis the ſame word in the <hi>Greek</hi> in all the three Verſes, though diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently rendred in our Tranſlation. How do they thus glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in God? 'Tis through Jeſus Chriſt, who hath broug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in this righteouſneſs for them, and by whoſe Death they were when Enemies reconciled to God, and by whom they have received that Atonement. They do glory before God in him only, in whom they are, and who is of God made righteouſneſs unto them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30, 31. and in the unchangeableneſs of the Love of God towards them in Chriſt, they do triumph even while they have before their eyes their own guiltineſs in themſelves, and how much mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter for Eternal condemnation there is in them; for it is upon Chriſt's not being ſpared or abated any thing but being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up and dying, and God's juſtifying (all which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94055:20"/>plainly ſpeak them in themſelves obnoxious to condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and worthy of Death) upon theſe things it is that the Apoſtle bottoms that challenge, and raiſeth that tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant perſuaſion, and Song of aſſurance which he there uttereth in the Name of all Believers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32, 33, 34, 35, 38, 39. Believers have given them beauty for aſhes, the oyl of joy for mourning, the garment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavineſs, and they do greatly rejoyce in the Lord, even in the Lord, who was angry with them, and their Souls are joyful in their God whom they know they have ſinned againſt. But how comes this to paſs? Is it becauſe their ſins are through tract of time out of Gods thoughts, and Memory? No, a thouſand years are with him but as one day. He is an Eternal God, and they are as freſh, and preſent before him, as if they were juſt then in committing. Is it becauſe God thinks better of their ſins than formerly he did when he frown'd upon them, and wrote bitter things againſt them? No, their ſins are as diſtaſteful to him, as much hated by him as ever they were, nor will he ever to Eternity have a better thought of any of them. Is it becauſe Believers are become more vain and ſenſeleſs and ſlightly-ſpirited than they were in thoſe former days of bitterneſs and anguiſh? No verily, they have more of the heart of Fleſh than they then had, and there is in them now a deeper ſenſe of the evil of ſin, and a deeper work of the Spirit of Humiliation, and more thorow thawings and meltings of heart before the face of God then ever. Whence is it then, and how comes it to paſs that Believers are made even in the view of their own end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſin and guiltineſs yet to triumph and rejoyce with Joy unſpeakable and full of Glory! It is hence, God hath cloathed them with the Garments of Salvation, he hath covered them with the robe of Righteouſneſs, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſpeaks, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.10. This righteouſneſs of Chriſt is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94055:21"/>upon them, and thence they have the conſolations of God, delighting their Souls, and abounding in them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, There are not only ſuch great and precious things injoyed by Believers while here, but there are alſo things high and glorious, laid up and reſerved for them hereafter, when they ſhall be here no more. There ſhall be a Glory revealed in them far beyond all compare with any of the afflictions that they meet with in this World, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. They are now indeed the Sons of God, and that is ſuch manner of Love, and ſo great that Men and Angels may ſtand and gaze and wonder at it: But though now already they be thus loved, nevertheleſs it doth not yet appear what they ſhall be. Only we know that when the only begotten of God, the Prince of Life, and Lord of Glory ſhall appear, then ſhall they appear with him in Glory, and they ſhall ſee him as he is, and they ſhall be made like him, even theſe vile Bodies ſhall by him be faſhioned like his own Glorious Body, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.4. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. And in that day the world ſhall ſee and know, and they themſelves ſhall everlaſtingly feel that Chriſt is in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and they in Chriſt, and he in them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.20. And that both Chriſt and the Father too have loved them as the Father hath loved Chriſt, and that very lo e wherewith the Father hath loved Chriſt himſelf ſhall be in them for ever. <hi>John</hi> 15.19. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.23, 26. But now if you ask as ſhe ſometimes did concerning another great work of love and wonder, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.34. How can theſe things ever be, ſeeing they are ſuch ſinful, ſuch guilty, ſuch vile, and loathſome, and hateful Creatures in themſelves: This Text, this Doctrine anſwers all in this one word, <hi>The righteouſneſs of Chriſt is through Faith unto them all, and upon them all without difference who do believe.</hi> Let your hearts anſwer and eccho back as <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ries</hi> there did, <hi>ver.</hi> 38, 45. <hi>Behold the handmaid of the Lord, be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94055:21"/>it to me according to thy word.</hi> Stagger not you at theſe great things as incredible, as impoſſible ever to be done for you who are ſo aſhamed of, and do ſo exceedingly abhor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> your ſelves, and who are worthy of nothing but to be rejected and abhorred of God eternally, but believe, take them in by Faith, and by Faith receive the gift of this righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and then there ſhall moſt aſſuredly be a performance unto you, even unto you, of thoſe things that have been told you from the Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:94055:22"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. iii. 22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Even the Righteouſneſs of God which is by Faith of Jeſus Chriſt unto all, and upon all them that believe, for there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Point of Doctrine obſerved from theſe words you may remember was to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Doctrine. <hi>There is a Righteouſneſs of God which is by Faith of Jeſus Chriſt unto all, and upon all without difference who do believe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Six things have been propoſed to be ſpoken to for the clearing up of the Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>What is this Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God, and why ſo called.</hi> 2 <hi>How it is unto and upon all that believe?</hi> 3. <hi>What is the import and meaning of that word,</hi> without difference? 4. <hi>What is this Faith of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> 5. <hi>What reference hath this faith unto this Righteouſneſs being on Believers?</hi> 6. <hi>Whence is all this, and how comes this about?</hi> Of theſe particulars I have already gone through the three former, and know not any need either to retract, or to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain further what was then delivered, ſo ſhall it go with your Souls, ſo will God deal with every one of you, as you receive or reject thoſe Truths of his.</p>
            <p>That which is now before me is thoſe other three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining particulars for the clearing up of the Doctrine, and the further application of it. And hereto I now addreſs my ſelf.</p>
            <p>Q. 4. <hi>VVhat is this Faith of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:94055:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By Faith of Jeſus Chriſt is meant Faith upon him, that Chriſt is the object, not the ſubject of it. Not that Chriſt is he that believes, but he on whom we believe. So is this manner of ſpeaking uſed elſewhere, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Knowing that a man is juſtified by the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt, we have believed in Jeſus Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And ſo ver. 20. <hi>I live by the Faith of the Son of God.</hi> So in <hi>Acts</hi> 3.16. <hi>By Faith in his Name.</hi> It is the ſame caſe and conſtruction in the <hi>Greek</hi> as it is here in the Text and in the <hi>Galatians,</hi> and might as well be rendred Faith of his Name. You have the like, <hi>Mark</hi> 11.22. <hi>Have Faith in God,</hi> or as your Margins tell you, <hi>Have the Faith of God.</hi> It might as well be rendred here <hi>Faith in Jeſus Chriſt</hi> as it is their <hi>Faith in God.</hi> The Grammer and the meaning is the ſame in both places. It is <hi>genitivus objecti,</hi> not <hi>efficient is</hi> or <hi>ſubjecti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It being then Faith on Chriſt, let us next conſider what this Faith is: And I ſhall briefly touch on three things concerning it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The ſubject of Faith is the heart of a convinced, broken-hearted, humbled ſinner.</hi> Faith is ſeated and acted in the heart. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. <hi>VVith the heart man believeth unto Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> And it is the heart of a convinced, contrite, humbled Sinner. Where there is not any conviction of Sin there is no Conviction of Righteouſneſs. For as the whole and well do not need, ſo they do not ſee and feel themſelves ſick and wounded unto Death will not ſeek to a Phyſician, nor commit themſelves into his hands. He that doth not ſee himſelf in danger of Death by the Avenger of Blood will not flee to Chriſt for refuge to lay hold upon him, which is the work of Faith, or that which the Soul doth in belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; as the Apoſtle ſets it forth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. The very nature of Faith and the Acting of the Soul in it, is ſuch as doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and include a ſight and ſenſe of Sin and Miſery, and an over-powering, practical, lively, heart-influencing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94055:23"/>of utter helpleſneſs in a mans ſelf, and unworthineſs to be helped by God. In believing the Soul looks on it ſelf as in a periſhing Condition, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.14, 16, 17, 19. as a poor and needy Friendleſs and Fatherleſs Creature, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.3. and betakes it ſelf to Soveraign Grace and Mercy. It believes <hi>that it may be juſtified, Gal.</hi> 2.16. which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes that it ſees it ſelf lyable to condemnation: Yea, it <hi>knows</hi> as the Apoſtle there ſpeaks, <hi>that men are not juſtified by the works of the Law,</hi> that is, in its believing it is under a particular and lively Conviction, that by the works of the Law neither any other, nor it ſelf ſhall ever be juſtified, and it is thereby influenced to ſeek to be juſtified by Chriſt in this way of believing. Not but that after Faith and Pardon, and a ſenſe of it too, there are deep humblings and meltings of God according to that promiſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.61, 63. and we ſee was in her, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.38. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs a truth it is, that Unhumbledneſs and Pride are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with true Faith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.44, and ſo alſo is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency and hardneſs of Heart, the Seed of the word of the Goſpel will never take root and grow up in ſuch an heart, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.32. and 13.20, 21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The object of Faith is Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> that is, <hi>the anointed Saviour,</hi> or the Name of Chriſt, as 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.23. and <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. that is, Chriſt as made known, and ſet forth and declared in the Goſpel. And in the Goſpel he is ſet forth as the Ordinance and Servant of God for ſaving Sinners of the Sons of Men. Chriſt is the next and immediate object of Faith, God is the ultimate Object of it. For by him we come to God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. and by him we do believe in God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The hearts acting towards this object in its believing is moſt properly in a way of truſt and dependence and affiance.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt, who is the Author and worker of Faith, and who beſt knows the Nature of it, doth in Scripture
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:94055:23"/>ſet it forth by great variety of expreſſions, ſome proper, ſome metaphorical. <hi>Truſting</hi> and <hi>believing</hi> in, are among the proper expreſſions whereby the Holy Ghoſt declares the Nature of Faith, and the acting of the Heart therein towards Chriſt and God by him. The former is uſed by him, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.12, 13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10. and 26.3, 4. and often elſewhere. The latter is uſed <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.6. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. and 6.29. and 14. 1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12 and in many other places. There are alſo ſome Metaphorical Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons uſed by the Holy Ghoſt to the ſame purpoſe. And as they are in their Nature apt and fit to let in a Light of Underſtanding into our Minds, and to guide them in their conceivings concerning the Nature of this Faith, through which the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt comes to be unto all, and upon all that believe: So the Holy Ghoſts uſing them, warrants us to uſe them in ſpeaking of and deſcribing Faith. To give ſome inſtances. Believing is called <hi>looking</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.22. and it implyes a <hi>looking</hi> to him with <hi>earneſt deſire</hi> and <hi>expectation.</hi> For that expreſſion in the <hi>Prophet,</hi> is taken from that Ordinance in <hi>Moſes, Numb.</hi> 21.8. where you find the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> directed when ſtung by the Fiery Serpents to <hi>took to</hi> the Brazen Serpent that they might not dye but live and be healed. Chriſt ſhows us that himſelf was ſhadowed and prefigured by that Brazen Serpent, <hi>John</hi> 3.14. and his death by the lifting of it up, <hi>John</hi> 12.32, 33. and accordingly by their <hi>looking to</hi> it, was <hi>believing</hi> taught, as Chriſt plainly intimates, <hi>John</hi> 3.15. And therefore as an <hi>Iſraetite</hi> who felt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſtung by the Fiery Serpents and dying, <hi>looked with ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs of expectation</hi> to the Brazen Serpent; in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner doth the Heart of a convinced Sinner work towards Chriſt in believing. Again, Believing is called <hi>coming</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. <hi>John</hi> 6.37, 44, 45. for in <hi>ver.</hi> 35. he had explained <hi>coming</hi> to him by <hi>believing</hi> on him. But
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94055:24"/>what manner of coming is it? Is it a dead, cold, careleſs coming? No, it is a coming with appetite and affection, as an hungry man comes to his Meat, and a thirſty man to drink; which alſo is Chriſts compariſon there. And thence elſewhere the ſame Spirit who is the worker of Faith in us, and under whoſe hand the Soul is conducted and doth act in its believing, calls it a <hi>fleeing unto Chriſt for refuge, to lay hold upon the hope ſet before us, Heb.</hi> 6.18. All the expreſſion ſets forth <hi>earneſtneſs</hi> in the Heart in its believing. For they are taken from the practiſe of one who finding himſelf in danger of Death from the Avenger of Blood, fled unto the City of Refuge (the Ordinance for which you may ſee <hi>Numb.</hi> 35.13, 15.) or from the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of a ſelf-convicted, ſelf-condemned Criminal among the <hi>Jewes,</hi> who fled to the Tabernacle and caught hold on the Horns of the Altar (as you ſee <hi>Joab</hi> did 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3.28.) even in like manner doth the Soul act in believing, it <hi>comes,</hi> it <hi>flees</hi> to Chriſt <hi>for refuge,</hi> it <hi>lays hold</hi> upon him. Moreover, Believing is called by the Holy Ghoſt <hi>commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> our Selves, and Souls, and Concerns unto Chriſt and God in him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.5. and 10.14. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.3. I know the word in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal in thoſe places is different, but ſo it is rendred by our Tranſlators, and that not amiſs. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> plainly ſhows that believing on Chriſt is a committing of our Souls unto him, when ſpeaking of himſelf he ſaith, <hi>I know whom I have believed, and know that he is able to keep that which I have committed to him,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. Laſtly, (for I will mention no more) Believing is called <hi>leaning, ſtaying, reſting,</hi> viz. on Chriſt and on God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10. This I conceive was taught them and us by that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance which injoyned him that brought the Sacrifice to lay his hand, or lean with his hand upon his Sacrifice, <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.10. <hi>Lev.</hi> 1.4. and 3.2, 8, 33. and 4.4, 15, 24, 29,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:94055:24"/>33. and 16.21. I know that Rite is by many interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as ſignifying the transferring or tranſlating of the Sin of him that brought the Sacrifice unto or upon the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice which was to be offer'd for him. But the laying of our Sins upon Chriſt is not our act but Gods, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.6. and the word uſed in <hi>Exodus</hi> and <hi>Leviticus</hi> doth ſignify a leaning with ſtreſs and might, and is rendred, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.8. <hi>lyeth hard,</hi> and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.2. <hi>beſet,</hi> that is, preſſed upon with force and ſtrength. And the Apoſtle (if I miſtake not the meaning of the place, which I think I do not) tells us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. that <hi>Faith towards God, or on God, is the doctrine of laying on of hands,</hi> that is, the thing taught by that Rite or Ceremony; even as <hi>repentance from dead works</hi> is the doctrine of, or thing taught by their <hi>Levitical waſhings,</hi> which I take to be there meant by Baptiſms. However it is manifeſt that the Holy Ghoſt frequently ſets forth <hi>believing</hi> by <hi>leaning, ſtaying, reſting,</hi> and words of like import. And very appoſite and lively Metaphors they are, for they do hold forth both the nature and the tendency of Faith. The Nature of Faith, inaſmuch as in believing the Soul doth make an adventure of it ſelf, and all its concernments for Eternity, upon Chriſt and this Righteouſneſs of his. Such an Adventure, that if Chriſt and his righteouſneſs ſhould fail it, it hath no other hopes or expectations, but muſt fall and periſh and ſink it ſelf for ever. And the tendency of Faith, namely that it tends to bring in eaſe and peace, repoſe and tranquillity, yea, Aſſurance, and humble, holy Security into the Soul. Or, as the Apoſtle expreſſeth it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13. it tends to the Souls being filled with all peace and joy; for the end of Faith to which it tends, is joy unſpeakable and full of Glory, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8, 9. The word uſed in that forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Rite which I ſaid ſignifies to lean upon with ſtreſs and weight doth alſo ſignify to ſuſteyn, ſupport, uphold.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:94055:25"/>and is often ſo tranſlated. It is ſuch a leaning and relying as brings in relief and ſupport, and on that account it very aptly ſets forth believing.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>VVhat is the reference that Faith hath unto this Righteouſneſs of Christs being upon them that believe?</hi> For the Text and Doctrine ſay it is <hi>through Faith</hi> unto them and upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. Some there are who (poſſibly out of a godly fear of giving too much in this matter to man, or any thing done by him,) ſeem to deny that Faith hath any reference unto Chriſts Righteouſneſs being upon us, ſave onely by way of diſcerning or evidence. And according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they ſeem to make Juſtification to be nothing elſe but Gods ſpeaking peace in the Conſcience of the Sinner, and cauſing it to ſee and hear what was done for him in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven long before. Poſſibly they might be led into that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake by the Expreſſion of ſome great Divines,<note place="margin">Rutherf. <hi>Exerc. de gr. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 24. Owen <hi>Append. againſt</hi> Biddle, <hi>p.</hi> 19. Bradſh. of Juſtific. <hi>C.</hi> 23. <hi>To.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp; C.</hi> 24. <hi>To.</hi> 15. Nort. Orth. Evang. <hi>pag.</hi> 311, 315, 317, 318, 322.</note> who are far from being <hi>Antinomians,</hi> that the Sentence of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is <hi>terminated on the ſinners Conſcience.</hi> Wherein I conceive they mean no more but that it is a ſentence of God ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in his Word, as that the Conſcience may and ought to receive it, and ſit down ſatisfied and acquieſcing in it. For ſurely to confound Juſtification and Aſſurance, and make them one and the ſame, muſt needs be a wide miſtake; when the Scripture plainly declares, that they may be ſeparated, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10. Though it is true, that Faith, if it be ſound and ſaving, doth tend towards Aſſurance or Peace of Conſcience, and that there is ſome kind of Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in all Faith, if it be the Faith of Gods Elect, Faith
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:94055:25"/>of the operation of God Namely, there is an aſſured ſatisfying perſwaſion in the heart concerning the Object of Faith, or the thing believed on. This kind of Aſſurance God requires in all acceptable Worſhip, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. and the Apoſtle tells us there was this Aſſurance in the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> at their firſt believing, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5. Nevertheleſs to make Faith to have no other influence unto our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or Chriſts Righteouſneſs being upon us, than to diſcern and ſee it, doth not come up unto the expreſſion of the Holy Ghoſt in the Text, where he ſaith it <hi>is</hi> upon us through Faith, not, it is <hi>ſeen</hi> or <hi>diſcerned</hi> to be upon us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of late ſome (chiefly <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>Semi-ſocinians,</hi> who reject the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing only the benefits or effects of it to be upon us, and communicated to us, but not the Righteouſneſs it ſelf) find much fault with that word <hi>inſtrument</hi> in this matter, and contend eagerly that the reſpect which Faith hath to the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt being on us, and to our Juſtification, muſt be expreſſed by the word <hi>condition.</hi> But this is not a Scriptural Word, and therefore we are at liberty to receive or to refuſe it, as it agrees or diſagrees with what the Scripture ſpeaks in this buſineſs. And the truth is, that word <hi>Condition</hi> is ambiguous and of an uncertain ſound and ſignification, and therefore there is danger in uſing it, for there may be deadly Poyſon under it; Becauſe there are many ſorts of Conditions; Some are valuable conſiderations, yea, ſome that are the price and procuring Cauſes of that whereof they are the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. <hi>Grevinchovius</hi> the <hi>Arminian</hi> will have Faith to be ſuch a condition, as that the foreſight thereof <hi>moves</hi> the Will of God as a Judge to give us the <hi>reward</hi> of Life. And another among our ſelves aſſerts, that all the benefits of the Covenant of Grace (among which ſurely Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94055:26"/>Adoption, the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt being upon us, and our being united to him, are none of the leaſt) are rewards given, not indeed <hi>for</hi> our believing, ſaith he, not by way of Merit, not of Debt, yet in way of <hi>reward.</hi> Another, who ſpeaks clearly and leſs covertly, ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, that God juſtifies and ſaves none but <hi>for</hi> their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving. And another who ſearched and ſaw as far as either of them, and ſpeaks out, ſaith plainly, that we are Pardon'd, Juſtified and Adopted to Eternal Life as a <hi>reward</hi> to Believers <hi>for</hi> their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience:</hi> And withal tells us in the ſame Book, that <hi>Reward and Merit are Relatives,</hi> ſo as that <hi>wherever there is Reward following, there Merit went before,</hi> and that <hi>there is no Reward, but it is a Reward of Merit.</hi> 'Tis true indeed, he will have the Merit of our repenting and believing, but a <hi>ſubordinate Merit,</hi> and Chriſt's the principal. But what is this better than the old Popiſh Notion, that Chriſt Merited that we might Merit, and we Merit in the virtue of his Blood, and by Gods Grace? And indeed he expreſly owns this Tenet of theirs. But ſurely this is another Goſpel, that we are pardoned, juſtified, adopted, and veſted in the Priviledges of the New Covenant Eſtate as a <hi>reward of</hi> or <hi>for</hi> our believing, repenting, or new obedience; and a Doctrine groſſer than many Learned Papiſts hold, as great Merit-mongers as they are; For they inſiſt upon it as one condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion requiſite unto Merit, that the Perſon Meriting the Reward muſt firſt be in a State of Grace and Favour with God; and therefore Juſtification and Adoption cannot be Merited by us, nor are conferred upon us as a reward of any thing that we do. Yea, methinks it is a very perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and Soul-deſtroying Error, if there be or ever have been any ſuch in the World. For if a Mans Heart be influenced by it, and moulded according to it in all his treating with God and applications to him for pardon of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:94055:26"/>Sin, and Juſtification and adoption, he is wholly led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide quite off from the way of the Goſpel, and it is utterly impoſſible he ſhould ever truely believe. For Faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives and looks for Union to Chriſt, intereſt in this righteouſneſs of his, pardon of Sin, Juſtification and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, not as a reward <hi>for</hi> or <hi>of</hi> any thing that we do, but meerly of Free Grace, and wholly for the ſake of Chriſt and his righteouſneſs. I conclude therefore that though this Word <hi>Condition</hi> may be uſed, and is ſo by ſome, in a ſound ſenſe, and with a good meaning, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Faith, and its reference to the righteouſneſs of Chriſt being upon us; yet it is neither convenient nor ſafe. For it may occaſion an unhappy ſtumbling, and a Soul-ruining miſtake. And therefore I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but joyn with that great Divine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Tho. Goodwin <hi>on Eph.</hi> 2. <hi>Serm.</hi> 22. <hi>p.</hi> 301.</note> who wiſheth it were laid aſide, and wholly diſuſed, becauſe there is danger in it, or at leaſt, (if men be impotently fond of the word) that it were both more ſoundly meant and better explained than it is by our preſent Contenders for it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The generality of all thoſe that own the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt being upon us, as that wherein we ſtand juſtified, have uſed to expreſs the influence of Faith there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by that word <hi>Inſtrument.</hi> So the <hi>Weſtminſter Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> do, both in their <hi>Confeſſion</hi> and in their <hi>Catechiſm.</hi> Nor have I ſeen any thing alledged againſt expreſſing it by that word, that amounts to any more but that the word is not ſtrictly and preciſely proper in the ſame ſenſe wherein it is uſed in other caſes; which for my part I will eaſily grant. But what then? <hi>Ars poſterior prioris utitur operâ. Artes in</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>concreſcunt.</hi> We muſt of neceſſity, and are warranted by the practiſe of the Holy Ghoſt to uſe Figures and Tropes in ſpeaking of and declaring the Truths of God. It is alſ readily granted that, the word <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:94055:27"/>is not found in Scripture uſed matter. But yet for all that it may be a word of the Holy Ghoſts Teaching; for it is ſuited and apt to declare, and let in into our Minds the true Notion and conception of what the Scripture declares to be the reference of Faith unto our Juſtification. The Scripture ſaith it is <hi>by</hi> and <hi>through</hi> and <hi>of</hi> Faith, yea, it ſaith that <hi>God juſtifies</hi> us <hi>by</hi> Faith and <hi>through</hi> Faith. I know no word that doth ſo well expreſs the work and uſe of Faith in this matter which the Holy Ghoſt ſets forth by receiving, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.11, 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.11, 17. where we are ſaid to <hi>receive</hi> Chriſt, and to receive his Righteouſneſs and the Atonement made thereby. An expreſſion that ſpeaks both our having it, or being poſſeſſed of it, and the means or way on our part, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is effected or brought about, <hi>viz.</hi> that it is by and in ſuch a like acting of our Hearts towards Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs, as anſwers the work of the Hand in taking and receiving a corporeal thing offer'd to us, and by our taking it made ours. For my part, as on the one hand I would not be needleſly tenacious of a word where we can as well retain and expreſs the Truth without it; ſo on the other hand, I cannot but obſerve, that all thoſe (even to a Man, not one as far as I remember to be excepted) who quarrel with that word <hi>inſtrument,</hi> and wrangle to bring in the word <hi>condition</hi> in this buſineſs of our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and Chriſts Righteouſneſs being upon us, do labour under that Covert to bring in withal a very weighty and momentous alteration in the ſubſtance of the Doctrine of the Goſpel: For they would alſo bring in other things, <hi>viz.</hi> Repentance and Love and new Obedience, as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of our Juſtification as well as Faith, and as the Righteouſneſs which is imputed to us, and wherein we ſtand. And they are generally for a <hi>conditional Redemption</hi> alſo, and many of them for a conditional Election too.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:94055:27"/>
            <p n="4">4. I ſhall therefore, waving thoſe diſſatisfying words ſet, before you what I conceive to be the Truth of God in this matter briefly in a few Propoſitions, concerning the refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that Faith hath unto the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon us. Onely premiſing two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That I am ſpeaking of <hi>poſſeſſion or actual injoyment of this righteouſneſs of Chriſt, not of right or title to it.</hi> Right and Poſſeſſion are different things, and therefore things of a different Nature, and may be one without the other.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rutherf.</hi> of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, p. <hi>231, 232.</hi>
               </note> Faith hath no influence, no not ſo much as in a way of inſtrumentality, to confer upon us a right and title to Chriſts Righteouſneſs, all the influence that Faith hath in this matter is onely unto our actual Poſſeſſion of it; which the Holy Ghoſt calls our <hi>having</hi> it, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. and here in the Text its <hi>being upon</hi> us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>This Poſſeſſion, or having this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> the reference of Faith whereunto I am ſpeaking of, <hi>is that having it which is unto Juſtification of Life, and that as the next and immediate effect of this Righteouſneſs being thus upon us.</hi> It is having it freely imputed to us, ſo as to ſtand in it before God for the preſent and everlaſting ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of our Perſons as righteous by it unto Eternal Life. It may be (and indeed is) upon us, as to ſome effects of it, and this not be through Faith, but unto Faith. For Faith is obtained for us by it, and beſtowed on us for the ſake of it. But its having an efficacy for us, ſo as to have ſome effects of it communicated to us, is indeed its operating for us and on us, but it is not its being upon us which the Text ſpeaks of. This righteouſneſs is one thing, the ſaving effects of it are another. The thing I am to ſpeak to is not what reference Faith hath to any of the effects of this righteouſneſs being wrought on us, but what reference it hath unto the being on us of this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:94055:28"/>it ſelf, and that by the free gift and valid imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God unto Juſtification of Lite.</p>
            <p>Having premiſed theſe two things, I ſhall deliver my ſelf touching this matter in Six Propoſitions.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Propoſ. 1. <hi>There is a reference or reſpect of connexion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Faith and this Righteouſneſs being upon us unto Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of Life.</hi> And this connexion is inviolable, and holds in all perſons. (I ſpeak of ſuch as are adult, for how it is upon Infants I now conſider not). Inſomuch as it is a certain Truth, that whoſoever believeth not, this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is not upon him; and whoſoever hath it upon him is a Believer. Having believed, and having this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, are ſo inſeparably connected and linked together, that where-ever there is one the other alſo is; and if there be not both there is neither. If thou haſt not believed with the Faith of Gods Elect, thy own Conſcience ought to paſs this Judgment on thee (for God in his Word doth it) that thou haſt not this righteouſneſs upon thee. And on the other hand, if thou haſt indeed believed with this Faith of the operation of God, and thy Conſcience know it, thou mayſt then conclude aſſuredly, that whatever thy Sins have been, or whatever thy defects and corruptions now be; yet this righteouſneſs of God is upon thee, thou haſt it, and thou doſt ſtand in it.</item>
               <item>Propoſ. 2. <hi>There is a reference of order between a mans be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, and this righteouſneſs being thus upon him.</hi> I do not ſpeak of an order of Time, but an order onely of Nature and Conſecution of the one upon the other. And ſuch an order there is among the Bleſſings and Benefits of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. For it is <hi>ordered in all things,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. all the concernments and bleſſings and benefits of it are wiſely and graciouſly diſpoſed and ranked by God. You may ſee it in other Inſtances. We are not firſt made Children and then pardon'd, but firſt pardoned and then adopted to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:94055:28"/>be Children. We are not firſt ſanctified and then juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but firſt juſtified, and then being juſtified we are ſanctified. Not that there is any ſpace of time between them, no they are as to time done together and at once; but yet there is an order of dependance and cauſality. Our being ſanctified is the Effect, not the Cauſe of our being juſtified, and our being juſtified the Cauſe, not the Effect of our being ſanctified. In like manner it is between our believing and this righteouſneſs being upon us for our Juſtification, or the change of our ſtate. It is through Faith that this righteouſneſs is upon us as the Text ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaith, and the Scripture every where ſpeaks, not contrarily.</item>
               <item>] Propoſ. 3. <hi>There is between our believing and this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs's being upon as a reference of cauſality.</hi> For Faith is a means thereof by the Ordination of God, and whatever God hath ordained as a means, hath ſome cauſal influence towards that whereof it is by him made a means. Thoſe Expreſſions of the Holy Ghoſt that we are juſtified <hi>by</hi> Faith, and <hi>through</hi> Faith, and this in the Text, that this righteouſneſs is upon Believers <hi>through</hi> Faith, do imply ſome kind of cauſality, nor do I ſee how they can be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, or a juſt account given of them without admitting ſome kind of cauſal influence and efficiency to be in Faith towards our <hi>having</hi> this righteouſneſs, or its being <hi>upon</hi> us. I hope you will not ſtumble at the word <hi>cauſality.</hi> All that call Faith an inſtrument do ſpeak as much as I mean, for <hi>inſtrumenta etiam in cauſis adjuvantibus connumerantur,</hi> Inſtruments are a ſort of Cauſes. Thoſe who are very tender in this Point and greatly averſe and watchful againſt aſcribing too much in our Juſtification unto any thing in us or done by us, yet do concerning the hand of Faith herein freely uſe thoſe words <hi>Cauſality, Efficiency,</hi> and <hi>inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal cauſe.</hi> See Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> of <hi>Juſtification, pag.</hi> 148, 149,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:94055:29"/>150, 151, 152, 153. Mr. <hi>Durham</hi> on <hi>Rev. digreſ.</hi> 11. and indeed it is the common language of all Proteſtants who own the imputation of the righteouſneſs of Chriſt unto us. I ſhall indeavour to clear it further in the following Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</item>
               <item>Propoſ. 4. <hi>This Cauſality of Faith unto the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt being upon us, is of the leaſt and loweſt kind.</hi> It is not at all by way of Merit or Deſert, nor is it by way of ſole Efficiency, no nor principal, but all its Efficiency or Influence herein is from Gods Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution or Ordination, and wholly by virtue thereof. And this Ordination or Conſtitution of God, is not that we ſhould have the righteouſneſs of Chriſt upon us either <hi>for</hi> or as a <hi>reward</hi> of our believing; No, far be ſuch a thought from us. But God having in Wiſdom and Grace made this inviolable Conſtitution, that this righteouſneſs ſhall be upon every one that believes, it doth actually take place upon particular perſons at their believing, and ſo this righteouſneſs is upon them <hi>through</hi> Faith. He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves out of the ſhade into the ſhine of the Sun, hereby comes to have the Sun beams fall upon him: But that removal of his hath no influence upon the Sun, nor doth any thing to draw down the beams of it upon him. So our believing hath no influence upon the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, it hath an influence onely unto its being upon us. Though our unbelief makes us unworthy of it, or of any the leaſt mercy, yet our believing is as far from making us worthy to have this righteouſneſs of Chriſt upon us, as our defective and defiled Obedience is from making us worthy of Eternal Glory.</item>
               <item>Propoſ. 5. <hi>The next and immediate influence of Faith in this matter is, that by it according to the conſtitution of God, our myſtical vital union with Chriſt is accompliſhed.</hi> Such an Union there is between Chriſt and Believers. They are ingrafted into him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.4, 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17, 23, 24.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:94055:29"/>Betrothed and married unto him, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. They do dwell in Chriſt, and have Chriſt dwelling in them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.56. This Union is brought about, effected and accompliſhed by our believing; and therefore we are ſaid to believe into Chriſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. and Faith is called a <hi>coming to him,</hi> a phraſe which implyes and holds forth, not onely that while we continue in Unbelief we are at a diſtance from Chriſt, and that Chriſt is the Object of Faith; but alſo that by believing, Chriſt and the Believer are brought together, if I may ſo expreſs it. As Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers dwell in Chriſt and Chriſt in them, ſo this is by their <hi>eating his fleſh and drinking his blood, or eating him,</hi> Joh. 6.47. with <hi>ver.</hi> 54, 56. In eating and drinking, the Food and the drink are incorporated and made one with the Body. By eating and drinking Chriſts Fleſh and Blood, he there means believing on him. The Metaphor is taken from their eating the <hi>Manna,</hi> and drinking of the <hi>Rook</hi> in the Wilderneſs; or from their eating and drinking of their Sacrifices, as you know they were by a poſitive Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance to do of ſome of them. Chriſt indeed firſt lays hold on us and joyns himſelf to us, and we being laid hold on and drawn by him, do cloſe with him, and ſo come to co-aleſce into one myſtical Perſon with Chriſt. This our vital Union with him is indeed begun on his part, in his laying hold on us in a preventing way, but it is compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and accompliſhed, and becomes mutual by our believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Now being thus made one with Chriſt, his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs comes to be upon us unto the Juſtification of Life by the Ordinance, Conſtitution and Donation of God. It is as we are thus in him, and made Members of him, that his righteouſneſs is upon us. As a baſe-born Beggar and Criminal comes to have the Honour of a Princeſs upon her by being Married and becoming one Fleſh with an high born Prince.</item>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:94055:30"/>
               <item>Propoſ. 6. <hi>Nevertheleſs this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt hath ſome operation on us as well as for us antecedently to our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving.</hi> It hath an operation for us. For it did make Atonement, procure our Peace and accompliſh our Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation unto God: Theſe things were done and finiſhed, they were perfected by Chriſt in his bringing in this righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs. It hath alſo an operation upon us before our believing. To ſay nothing of Gods forbearing us, and ſhowing forth all long ſuffering toward us during all the days of our vanity and madneſs of heart, nor of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excellent Mercies given to us then, which when Grace comes to be grafted on them become very ſerviceable for the furtherance of our Salvation, becauſe it is not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo clear that theſe things which are not of a ſaving Nature, and which are injoyed by us while we are not under the bond of the Covenant, nor living Members of Chriſt, are procured for us by his righteouſneſs: This is certain and plain, that the Spirit, and Faith it ſelf are procured for us by, and given to us for this righteouſneſs, which is unto Juſtification upon us through Faith, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. Faith is purchaſed for us by it, and our juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is purchaſed by it, and both of them abſolutely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. And it may alſo be ſaid, that becauſe Juſtification is abſolutely procured by this righteouſneſs, therefore alſo Faith, being procured for us by the ſame righteouſneſs, is for the ſake of it given to us; that being the way ordained of God for our being juſtified, and it being a Mercy pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to the Elect, and a Mercy that hath Salvation accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying it, and a leading part of the application of Chriſt. This poſſibly may be one thing that hath occaſioned ſome to ſay that our Juſtification is rather the condition of our having Faith given us, than our Faith the condition of our Juſtification. I conceive they mean, that if Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had not been abſolutely procured and obtained for the Elect, Faith would never have been either given them or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:94055:30"/>obtained for them. However, moſt certain and undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able it is, that this Righteouſneſs operates on us antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently unto our believing, becauſe that preventing Grace and work of the Spirit, whereby Faith is wrought in us, are the effects of this Righteouſneſs, as being procured by it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, Two Things follow, which I will briefly note, for the further clearing up this whole Matter, and then paſs on to the laſt Enquiry propoſed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Our being juſtified is not the next or immediate effect or conſequence of our believing, but of Chriſts Righteouſneſs being upon us.</hi> For between our believing, and our being juſtified, there comes in our co-aleſcing into one Myſtical Perſon with Chriſt by this Vital Union, and our having his righteouſneſs upon us unto the Juſtification of Life: Which latter is the next fruit and conſequent of that our union to him, or being in him. His righteouſneſs is upon us as we are Members of him, and do ſtand in him: And this our union to him is brought about, and accompliſhed upon, and by our believing. Union to Chriſt goes before Communion with him. Union is the immediate conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of Faith. Our having this righteouſneſs upon us is one of the firſt things <hi>in</hi> our Communion with Chriſt. We are firſt <hi>in</hi> Chriſt, and ſo have him <hi>made righteouſneſs</hi> to us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Our Faith hath no hand in working out this righteouſneſs for us, nor is it any part thereof.</hi> The righteouſneſs of Chriſt is a garment, a robe wherewith Believers are cloathed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.13, 14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.8. But our Faith neither is a part of it, nor ever took ſtitch in it. The Apoſtle here in the Text doth not ſay this righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God <hi>is by</hi> or <hi>through</hi> Faith, or that it conſiſts either in whole, or in part, <hi>in</hi> Faith, but that it <hi>is upon us through faith.</hi> Wherein he plainly diſtinguiſheth between this righteouſneſs and our believing, and tells us it is the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:94055:31"/>namely, this righteouſneſs of God which is upon us unto juſtification of life, whereas the latter, namely faith, is <hi>within</hi> us, not <hi>upon</hi> us.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 6 <hi>How comes this about, and whence is it, that this righteouſneſs is through faith unto and upon all that believe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Enquiry leads me to lay open before you ſomething of the deep Counſels of the Wiſdom and Grace of God, in the Plot of our Salvation. I ſhall content my ſelf onely to point a little at the Heads of Things, telling you the Story of it from its firſt and higheſt Original, in theſe Seven Steps.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God the Father from Eternity begat his Son, the ſecond Perſon in the Trinity, and loving him with an infinite Love, deſigned a ſpecial Revenue of Glory, and Honour, and Praiſe, unto him, as from all his Creatures in their kind and way, ſo more eminently from and in a certain number of Mankind:</hi> Even thoſe whom he choſe in him <hi>before the</hi> Foundation of the World, that they ſhould be holy and without blame before him in love, having predeſtinated them unto the Adoption of Children by Jeſus Chriſt to himſelf, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the good pleaſure of his Will, unto the praiſe of the Glory of his Grace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.22, 23, 24-30. The End and Upſhot, and laſt iſſue that all his Counſels about them come to is this, that they may be brought to the acknowledgment of the Son of God, and he and his Father be Admired and Glorified by and in them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.13. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10, 12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.11, 12, 13, 14. For they were made for him, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>God hath ordained two more eminent ways for this end of bringing in a Revenue of Gl ry unto his Son, in the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Elect,</hi> viz. <hi>That he ſhall do all with God for them, and that he ſhall be all from God unto them.</hi> And hence as he had choſen them in Chriſt, ſo he gave them unto
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:94055:31"/>Chriſt, and that from Everlaſting to be an Head and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.2, 6, 9, 10. and 6.37, 39. And thence Chriſt ſtands engaged for them, and charged with them before God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.38, 39, 40. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.16. And God beholding them in Chriſt, is fully at reſt, and infinitely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted, and therefore ſpeaks as glorying and triumphing in this counſel of his, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.19.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though this was in the heart of God from Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and thus conſulted and agreed on between the Father and the Son; <hi>y t God made mankind, and among them the Elect in ſuch an eſtate, as that they needed not Chriſts ſo interpoſing between God and them, nor indeed were they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of it,</hi> being conſtituted under another head, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der another Covenant, which had nothing in it of Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs, either to be brought in for them, or to be apply'd to them. And indeed it became God to put his rational Creature perfect out of his hand, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.27. It was ſuitable to his Wiſdom, Holyneſs, and Goodneſs, that if he made a rational Creature he ſhould be made ſinleſs and holy, and in a ſtate of friendſhip with God. For elſe ſin would have been God's work (which is impoſſible) and the breach have begun on God's part, which would not have been meet, for then Mans deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction would not have been of himſelf, nor could God have beheld the works of his hands, and have pronounced con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them all that they were very good, nor could he have reſted and rejoyced in them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>All mankind, even the Elect who are given to Chriſt, as they were at firſt conſtituted under</hi> Adam, <hi>ſo they as well as o hers fell in him, and were plunged into ruine and death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing involved in the guilt of his diſobedience.</hi> In him they ſinned, and in him they dyed, though the Son of God had undertaken for them, and ſtood charged with them from Eternity. For his undertaking for them was not to keep
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:94055:32"/>them from falling into a ſtate of Sin and Death, but when fallen into it, to bring them out of that Eſtate unto Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life. Neither was his being charged with them to operate upon them till the time appointed for it; which was not till they ſhould be plunged into Guilt and Death, ſo as neither they themſelves, not any meer Creature could recover them out of that Eſtate, and raiſe them up unto that happineſs to which they were appointed.</p>
            <p>This fall of the Elect into a ſtate of Sin, and Death, and Wrath may poſſibly ſeem ſomewhat remote from the point in hand: But it is not. For hereby a Door is opened for the Son of God to ſtep in, and do all with God for them, and be all unto them, and that from God. All, I ſay, that in this ruined, periſhing condition they need to bring them to that height of Happyneſs to which they were fore-ordained in the great Love of God to them, and unto Chriſt his Son. So that as Chriſt ſpeaks of the blindneſs of him who was blind from the Womb, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.3. That it was that the works of God might be made manifeſt in him; we may ſay of this fall of the Elect, it was in the Counſel of God deſigned to this end, that the depths of the Riches of the Knowledge, and Wiſdom, and Grace, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God might be made manifeſt in them: And as Chriſt ſpeaks of <hi>Lazarus</hi> his ſickneſs and dying, <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.4. That it was not unto Death, meaning it was not that he ſhould abide in a ſtate of Death, ſo muſt we ſay of this falling of the Elect into a State of Spiritual Death in Sin and Treſpaſſes; it is not unto Death for ever, but for the Glory of God, that the Son of God might be glorified in recovering them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>In order unto the recovery and Salvation of the Elect by Chriſt, and his being glorified therein, God hath in infinite wiſdom ordained a double <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion between Chriſt and them, or two ways of their being in him.</hi> The one, that Chriſt may ſtand before God, and tranſact for them with God in <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:94055:32"/>as a publick Perſon: The other, that he may be all to them from God, wherein what he hath obtained and received for them comes to be <hi>unto</hi> them, <hi>upon</hi> them, and <hi>in</hi> them, in the <hi>Application</hi> of that Redemption. The one of theſe Unions between Chriſt and us I may call an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in Law,</hi> the other a <hi>Vital <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> I confeſs the terms are not ſo appoſite as I could wiſh, But I know not any better, and in that penury of words under which we labour, we muſt ſometimes take up with terms which are not altogether to our minds. I call the one an <hi>V;nion in Law,</hi> becauſe by it Chriſt and the Elect are after a ſort made <hi>one Perſon in Law,</hi> and he bears a relation to them ſo as that they are ſaid to be <hi>in him</hi> in his reviving, riſing from the dead, and ſitting in Heavenly places, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.5, 6. and that Grace, which we in our own perſons are in time made partakers of, is ſaid to have been <hi>given us in him</hi> before the World began, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. The other I call a <hi>Vital <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> becauſe there is in it a mutual Living acting on each other between Chriſt and us. Chriſt apprehends or lays hold on us, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.11. He draws us, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.32. and we being drawn do come to him, and cloſe in with him. Both theſe Unions are Myſtical, that is Spiritual, Sacred and Sublime, both of them are of Grace, free and meer Grace, and therefore Supernatural, and therefore of Supercreation Grace. Both of them are for the Honour of Chriſt the Son of God, and both of them make for inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Life unto all the Seed, unto all that are given unto Chriſt, unto all the Elect of God: For theſe are but diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent adjuncts of the ſame ſubject. Yet between theſe Unions there is a manifold and manifeſt difference. The one was from everlaſting, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. the other in time, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. The one is of all the Elect at once and together; the other is not ſo, but brought about in the ſeveral ſeaſons determined on between the Father and the Son, namely,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:94055:33"/>when the day of their Power, and the time of their Love dawns upon this and that particular Perfon; for ſome are in Chriſt before others with that Vital Union, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.7. The one is compleated and perfected in the tranſaction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Chriſt concerning us, without any thing done on us, or in us, or by us; which cannot be ſaid of the other, for in it, and indeed in order to the effecting it, Chriſt lays hold on us. Moreover, the one, I mean that which I call <hi>Vital <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is reciprocal or mutual, in it not only we are in Chriſt, but he is alſo in us, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.20. and 15.4. and 17.23. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.7. In this Union there is a mutual in-being between Chriſt and Believers. But that other Union, which I called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in Law,</hi> is not in like manner mutual; for though we are ſaid to be <hi>in Chriſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of that publick capacity and common relation to us all that he ſtands in, yet till the <hi>Vital <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> between Chriſt and us is effected, it cannot be ſaid that he is <hi>in us.</hi> And laſtly theſe two Unions ſtand affected one to another as cauſe and effect. The former, namely that which I call <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in Law</hi> between Chriſt and us is the cauſe of the latter, namely of our being brought into that <hi>Vital <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> to him. And hence the former is the rule and meaſure of the latter, the latter is extended to all thoſe, and to thoſe only who are compriſed within the former, and it is in the vertue and cauſal efficacy of the former that the latter is brought about and accompliſhed.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Of this latter,</hi> viz. <hi>Vital <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion between Chriſt and us, Faith is the means on our ſide.</hi> Hence appears a further reaſon why it may well be called a Vital Union: Both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in its effecting there is a vital touch, as I may ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and us, and a claſping each on other; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo becauſe by, and in this Union unto Chriſt, we are brought immediately into a ſtate of Spiritual Life, firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative in Juſtification and Adoption, and then and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:94055:33"/>qualitative or transformative in Sanctification and Comfort, which are Glory begun, and ſhall be perfected hereafter. Hence it is that ſome Divines (and thoſe no mean ones for Spiritual Light and Judgment,) make Faith to be <hi>actus medii ut ſimus in vivis,</hi> rather than <hi>actus vitae quâ in vivis jam conſtituti vivimu,</hi> the means and way of our being made Spiritually alive, rather than our acting Life as being already brought into a ſtate of Life. As the Bodies cloſing with, and claſping hold on the Soul by the animal Spirits, which are corporeal things, is rather the means of Natural Life, than an Act of Life it ſelf. And the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſeems to be countenanced by the Scripture, which makes believing one thing, and Life another, and Faith the means of Life. See <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.40. and 6.53, 54, 57. and 20.31. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. However this is plain and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that <hi>he who hath the Son hath Life, and he that hath not the Son, hath not Life,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.12. and that we in our believing do receive Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. Faith being our cloſing with him in that conjugal Covenant, and Relation in which we are and ſtand vitally united to him.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>It being the proper uſe of Faith to be the means of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us thus unto Chriſt, and its proper Nature to reſt upon Chriſt for all, and to receive all from Chriſt, the Crown of all is hereby ſet upon the head of Christ, and to flouriſh there for ever.</hi> And thus you ſee how the grand original deſign of God to bring in a Revenue of ſingular Honour, and Praiſe, and Glory unto his Son Chriſt, is in this way brought about, accompliſhed and fulfilled. For, this Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt being upon us through Faith, it glorifies Chriſt in that he is made all unto us in our acceptance with God as righteous to Eternal Life. And indeed Faith is ſuch a Grace, as that there is in its Nature a ſingular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and fitneſs to give Glory unto Chriſt. This will be made apparent by conſidering theſe two things.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:94055:34"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Faith is a going out of our ſelves unto Chriſt for all.</hi> It is a going out of our ſelves as Indigent, miſerable, and periſhing. And to whom do we in believing go, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt? Faith therefore gives him the Glory of having in him a fulneſs of ſuitable ſufficiency for Sinners in our guilty, ruined Condition. And what do we go to him for? It is for all that we need. Being guilty and under Condemnation, we go to him for Righteouſneſs unto Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of Life, and thence Faith is ſaid to be in his Blood, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. Being utterly without ſtrength, and dead in ſins, we go to him for ſtrength, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.24. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing frail and mutable as Creatures, and having unſteadfaſt, treacherous hearts as Sinners, we go to him for Everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Righteouſneſs, and for eſtabliſhment in himſelf by an unchangeable Ordinance, and conſtant never-failing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences, that is, in one word, for Eternal Life. Thus as the Son of God is in himſelf a Perſon of infinitely higher Excellency than the <hi>firſt Adam,</hi> and a better Head unto all his Seed than the <hi>firſt Adam</hi> was: So Faith acknowledgeth him to be an Head far better than <hi>Adam</hi> beyond all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, and gives him the Glory of it accordingly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Faith is a prime and principal part of our being confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the image of the Son of God.</hi> Suppoſe that the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Grace begotten and created in us in Regeneration do contain in it the habit of Faith (which I will not now call in queſtion nor determine) yet this is manifeſt, that in our acting Faith we cannot ſo well and congruouſly be ſaid to act like God, as to act like Chriſt. For God never acted Faith, but Chriſt did, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.13. and was ſo open and frequent in the profeſſion of it, that his Adverſaries took notice of it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.7, 8. He owned and profeſſed that he lived by the Father, as we by Faith do live by him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.57. Though he be God by Nature and of himſelf, yet as Mediator he lives by the Father, and the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:94055:34"/>Humane Nature of Chriſt lives and ſubſiſ Perſon, leaning on the Eternal Deity of the Son of God, it hath its ſubſiſtence in the boſom of the God head. We in believing do herein imitate Chriſt after our manner and meaſure, and according to that unmeaſurable diſtance and diſproportion that is between him and us. We lean and live on Chriſt, and fetch all from him and from God through him. But he is the firſt Pattern and Original Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of believing; both becauſe he lived a Life of Faith, and becauſe the Humane Nature of Chriſt leans on the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head in the Son, and hath the Eternal Power of the Deity claſping about it, and holding it in that Union. After ſomewhat of a ſimilitudinary way, though with great diſſimilitude and diſparity do we by Faith lean and live upon Chriſt, and on God in and through him, the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Power of the Godhead in Chriſt (and not ſo much the ſtrength of any created principle of Grace in us) holding our hearts unto him, and cauſing them for ever to li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e upon him.</p>
            <p>USE 1. <hi>Here we may ſee the certain perpetuity of a Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers State, and the ground thereof.</hi> The Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is upon him through Faith. His Eſtate therefore is not, cannot be, undecided, and in ſuſpenſe. They who deny or conſider not that this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is through Faith upon all that believe, and look only to the falſeneſs and ſlipperineſs of our hearts, and either imagin ſome other way then through Faith for its being up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, or hold that we ſtand not in it, but in our own Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience or Faith, as our Righteouſneſs before God; it is no marvel if they be for Believers falling away from Grace. Their Darkneſs and Error in thoſe other great Principles of the Goſpel naturally leads and betrays them to this uncomfortable, unevangelical, and racking Error
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:94055:35"/>alſo, that a Believers State is in ſuſpenſe and undecided. But 'tis a plain caſe, They upon whom the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is, they are not in a State of ſuſpenſe, their State is not undecided: But ſo it is with all that believe. It is true indeed, if Believers ſtood in their own Obedience, and in their perſevering therein, ſo as to have their State de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on them, it might well be uncertain, and muſt be in ſuſpenſe and undecided till their laſt breath. But their continuance in Obedience, and the not failing of their Faith, is one of the Priviledges of their Eſtate, and the Effect or Fruit of their having this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt upon them, and not the means or cauſe thereof. But it may be you will ask, if it be not in ſuſpenſe and undeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, where is it decided? I anſwer; It is not always deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their own Conſciences, they may poſſibly be in the dark about it, and wofully toſſed with weary fluctuations between hope and fear concerning their own Eſtate. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I mean that it is decided before Men. The work and walk of a true Believer may poſſibly under the prevailing of Corruption and Temptation, and under Gods Dereli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, be ſuch as to make him look in the Eyes of Men like a graceleſs Caſt-away. Nor is it ſo publickly and ſo ſolemnly decided before all the World of Men and Angels, as it ſhall be at the great Day. But yet decided it is, and put out of ſuſpenſe. Where? In the Court of Heaven, where God ſits as a Judge paſſing Sentence concerning the Spiritual Eſtate of all Men. I mean his word, his written word, that's the Court of Heaven, there are Men condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and there they are juſtifyed, in the word God ſits as a Judge, pronouncing and paſſing Sentence concerning Mens Eſtates. There he pronounceth a Sentence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation upon all that are out of Chriſt, and there he pronounceth a Sentence of Justification unto all, and upon all that are in Chriſt by Faith. This I mean by the Court
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:94055:35"/>of Heaven. We ſhould take heed in this matter of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our thoughts vaniſh into Airy Speculations and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of I know not what Voices and Proclamations made in Heaven in the hearing of Saints and Angels, juſt as there is here on Earth among Men, when Perſons ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned are acquitted. The Scripture tells us not of any ſuch thing, though it tells us indeed there is Joy in Heaven over a Sinner that repents, and though it be made known to Angels when the Eſtate of an Elect here below is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, yet this is not Gods juſtifying of him, but his revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to them his being juſtified. Gods juſtifying us is in and by his word; what the Word ſpeaks God ſpeaks, and there is the Eſtate of every one that believes in Chriſt put out of ſuſpenſe for ever, and immutably and eternally decided. For there is an Unchangeable, Everlaſting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, that the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is and ſhall be upon every one that believeth in him. Now he with whom God is immutably and everlaſtingly well-pleaſed his State certainly is not in ſuſpence and undecided. But ſo is God pleaſed in Chriſt with every one that is in him by Faith, for this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is unto and upon every Believer.</p>
            <p>USE 2. This Doctrine ſpeaks <hi>Conviction unto all that are in their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief.</hi> You may here ſee, you ſhould here read that your Eſtate is wretched and woful; for the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is not upon you, it is only upon thoſe who do believe, and upon none elſe: And it is upon them through Faith; but you are without Faith, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have not this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt upon you. And if his Righteouſneſs be not upon you, the Wrath of God, and the Curſe of the Law, even of the violated broken Law are upon you, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3 10. For if this Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt be not upon you, your Sins are upon you,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:94055:36"/>the guilt of them all is upon you. As it is ſaid of thoſe Tyrants and Terrors in the Land of the Living in their day, that they lay down in their Graves with their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities upon their Bones, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32.27. So it muſt be ſaid of you, and it ſhould be believed by you of you ſelves, that you walk up and down among the Living with all your Iniquities upon you; and if you dye in this Faithleſs Condition, your Souls ſhall go down to Hell with all the uncircumciſed and wicked of the World, and the guilt of your Iniquities will be upon you for ever and ever. And it is very fearful and overwhelming guilt that is upon you. For there is the guilt of innumerable actual ſins of thy own perpetration, in Deed, in Word, in Thought; and ſome of them are hainous and amazing: Ask thy Conſcience elſe. And there is upon thee moreover the guilt of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved, defiled Nature by that exceeding ſinful ſin which dwelleth in thee, a ſort of ſin that hath a fulneſs of evil in it, and exceſſive madneſs of heart, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.3. it hath in it Infidelity, and Atheiſme, and Blaſphemy, and Contempt of God, and Enmity a gainſt him; and alſo all the flagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious atrocious wickedneſs againſt the ſecond Table that ever was committed by any of the Children of Men; and moreover all that audaciouſneſs and outrage which ever broke forth in any of the Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> in their ſinning. Such an one art thou in thy Heart and Nature before God, and therefore in his judgment (and his judgment is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to truth) guilty before him concerning all theſe things, though perhaps thou haſt never felt many of them ſtirring in thy boſom. And moreover there is upon thee the guilt of thy firſt Fathers ſinning and diſobedience; when he turned Rebel againſt God, thou waſt involved in that woful deed of his, and guilt and condemnation is upon the thereby, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18, 19. and from that ſin of thy firſt Father thou canſt never be diſcharged and juſtified, unleſs
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:94055:36"/>this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt be upon thee through Faith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.27. And laſtly, over and above the guilt of all theſe ſins, there is alſo upon thee the guilt of diſobeying the Goſpel in refuſing and deſpiſing this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt tender'd and brought near unto thee, when thou art in ſuch a loſt, and periſhing, and forlorne Condition: And verily this is an heavy and an overwhelming guilt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peradded unto all the reſt. You ſhould take in Convictions of your condemned, Condition, and that the Wrath of God abideth on you, and will do ſo as long as you continue in unbelief. Do not flatter your ſelves and delude your own Conſciences, by ſaying, I have mourned, and I have wept bitterly for my ſins, and over my poor Soul, and I have left them, and amended and reformed my Life, and I thank God I walk ſo and ſo, blameleſly and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarily. Be it ſo, yet let me put theſe two Demands to thy Conſcience. 1. Are theſe things the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt? And 2. Are they Faith? If they be not the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, they can never juſtifie thee from any the leaſt ſin: And if they be not Faith, the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt will never be upon thee <hi>by</hi> or <hi>thorow</hi> them. The Scripture no where ſaith that the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt is upon us through our repenting, not yet through our amending and reforming; no, nor through any works of Righteouſneſs and Obedience that we have done or can do. No, this is the Priviledge, Prerogative, and peculiar Office of Faith. True it is, theſe things are thy bounden Duties, God will damn thee for neglecting them: But yet as true and as certain it is, that they neither are the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, nor will they intitle thee to it, and intereſt thee in it. Know therefore that though thou couldſt mourn Rivers of Tears, or Seas of Bloody though thou couldſt amend thy Life, and reform thy way, and thy heart too, ſo as never more to ſin and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:94055:37"/>though for the time paſt of thy Life thou hadſt, and for all the time to come ſhouldſt live like a Saint dropt down from Heaven, and walk up and down in the World like an Angel in fleſh, ſhine, and ſparkle, and glitter among the Sons of God, yet as all this is not the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, ſo neither would the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt be upon thee through all theſe things, for they are not Faith. Thou art therefore in a ſtate of Condemnation, and the Wrath of God abides upon thee, and will do ſo as long as thou continueſt without Faith.</p>
            <p>USE 3. This Doctrine ſpeaks earneſt <hi>exhortation to get Faith, to believe.</hi> And it ſpeaks to you all, one and other, for you all ſtand in need of this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt to be upon you, the very leaſt ſinner among you all, as well as the greateſt. As the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſometime ſaid to <hi>Peter, Gal.</hi> 2.15, 16. <hi>We who are Jews by Nature, and not ſinners of the Gentiles, knowing that a man is not juſtified by the works of the Law, but by the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt, even we have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in Jeſus Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the works of the law: for by the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rks of the law ſhall no fleſh be juſtified:</hi> So I ſay to you that are not ſuch grievous and atrocious ſinners as ſome others are, you as well as the greateſt Sinners muſt believe in Jeſus Chriſt that you may be juſtified. And much more you whoſe own Conſciences neither do nor can make any other judgment of you, but that you are among the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chief of Sinners, Sinners before the Lord exceedingly, O do you get Faith, See that you believe. For in this way it will come to paſs that the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt ſhall be upon you, and in no way, by no means, unleſs you believe. You may try other courſes, you may gad about to change your way from foul to clean, from care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and looſe and prophane, to ſtrict, and ſerious, and circumſpect, but though you waſh you with Nitre,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:94055:37"/>and take you much Soap; yet your Iniquities will ſtand marked before the Lord, your guilt, the guilt of all your ſins wilt ſtill be upon you. You may take up the practiſe of Duties and abound therein, you may attain much light in Spiritual things, and become Eminent in Gifts: You may walk blameleſly in the Eye of the World, you may live in the fellowſhip of Saints, and in the obſervance of the Ordinances of God in the pureſt way of their Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration upon earth, and yet be without this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt upon you: For theſe are not Faith. It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a prepoſterous courſe to begin with taking up of Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties without looking after Faith; nay, it is an errour in the Foundation, and a building on the Sand: All your buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Duties, and Profeſſion, and Hopes will fall down, and the fall thereof will be great and fearful. Yet I fear it is the overſight and errour of many Profeſſors among us at this day, but it is a fatal and Soul-ruining one. My advice and Exhortation to you therefore is, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you do in the concernments of your Souls look to it that you believe. Whatever you neglect, neglect not getting Faith: Yea look to it in the firſt place. Thus your Teachers ſhould inſtruct and lead you: This is the Apoſtles direction unto <hi>Titus,</hi> that he ſhould teach them that have believed, to be careful to maintain, or to excel in good works, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.8. not to teach and preſs Sinners in their unbelief to fall to doing good works firſt, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look believing wholly, or to <hi>poſtpone</hi> it after them. And thus you ſhould practiſe, elſe you labour in the fire, and weary your ſelves in very vanity, for all your pain, and toil, and doing will not bring it about that the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt ſhall be upon you, for they are not Faith. But through Faith that Righteouſneſs will be upon you, and being upon you, it will produce good works, and both your Works and your Perſons be accepted, your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:94055:38"/>firſt, and then your Works. And if you believe, this Righteouſneſs ſhall certainly be upon you, and you ſhall be accepted and made Righteous in it, how many, or how heinous ſoever your ſins have been, or how great ſoever and amazing to your Conſciences your guilt be. For it is through Faith, and net through works of Obedience that it is unto all, and upon all without difference who do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. Therefore look to it that you do indeed believe, look to it that your Faith be the Faith of God's Elect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. This Doctrine ſpeaks <hi>to Believers, and to you it ſhows how you ſhould live and walk before God, ſo as to pleaſe, injoy and glorifie him.</hi> I will inſtance in three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>You ſhould walk holily in all new Obedience.</hi> If you be redeemed and delivered from Condemnation and Death (as verily you are if this Righteouſneſs be upon you) it is that you might ſerve the Lord <hi>without fear,</hi> ſlaviſh legal fear, <hi>in holineſs and righteouſneſs</hi> in all the Duties required both in the Firſt and Second Table of the Law, and that <hi>before him</hi> in ſincerity and uprightneſs of Heart, as in his ſight; and all this not in a fit only, or for a while, but <hi>all the</hi> days of your lives, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74, 75. This Love, this Grace of Chriſt, ſhould conſtrain you and make you thus judge, <hi>That if one dyed for all, then thoſe all have dyed,</hi> namely unto ſin; and he <hi>dyed that they which live ſhould not henceforth live unto themſelves, but unto him who dyed for them and roſe again</hi> for their Juſtification, and that they might riſe unto newneſs of life, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15. Thus the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> alſo argues, preſſing it upon Believers to <hi>be holy in all manner of converſation, even as he who hath called you is holy:</hi> And the ground upon which he inforceth it is this, becauſe they are redeemed with the precious Blood of Chriſt. See 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.14, 15, 16, 18, 19.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:94055:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>You ſhould walk humbly alſo as well as holily.</hi> This God doth require, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8. for you ſtand accepted, not in your ſelves, nor in any Works of Righteouſneſs that you have done, but wholly in the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt that is upon you through Faith. Therefore when you have done all, and attained, to the utmoſt, you ſhould ſtill be humble, and ſay you are unprofitable ſervants; <hi>Luke</hi> 17.10. For all your obedience and conformity to the Law avails no more to juſtifie you than your worſt ſins do; and you ſhould look on your beſt performances and your worſt ſins even with the ſame eye in the buſineſs of Juſtification. Believers do own that all their beſt Righteouſneſs is as to their Juſtification but as filthy rags, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6. and true Converts have the like, and can have no worſe thoughts of their worſt ſins, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.22. Labour you ſhould and abound in the work of the Lord; not to work out a Righteouſneſs to ſtand juſtified in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God: No, God forbid ſuch a thought ſhould ever be entertained by any Believer. I do not think the Saints in Heaven would be willing to exchange and put off the Robe of Chriſts Righteouſneſs to ſtand before God for acceptance in that perfect and ſpotleſs Holineſs to which they have there attained. Much leſs ſhould any Believer be willing to ſtand and continue in a juſtified eſtate by his own imperfect defective and ſtained Obedience. Neither indeed can I ſee how ſuch a frame of Heart can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with true Faith. But obey you ſhould becauſe you have a Righteouſneſs upon you, in compariſon and in competition wherewith the Righteouſneſs of Men and Angels is to be deſpiſed. Obey therefore to the utmoſt, but look away from it when you have ſo done. Obey, not to acquire or continue to your ſelves an intereſt in this Righteouſneſs, much leſs to be your Righteouſneſs before God, but that you may ſhow forth the Praiſes of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:94055:39"/>him who hath called you into Fellowſhip with his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>You ſhould alſo walk comfortably and rejoyſingly as well as holily and humbly.</hi> For you are made accepted in the beloved. Standing in this Righteouſneſs, having it upon you through Faith, you may, you ſhould rejoyſe and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, not in your ſelves on any performances of yours, or Graces inhering in you, but in the Lord in whom you have both Righteouſneſs and Strength: For the Lord hath ſworn that in him ſhould all the ſeed of <hi>Iſrael</hi> be juſtified and glory; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.23, 24, 25. Having by Faith received the atonement, you may glory even in his preſence, of whom you are in Chriſt Jeſus, who is of God made unto you Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification and Redemption, and you made the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God in him, that he that gloryeth ſhould glory in the Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THere are two Paſſages in the foregoing Sermons which have been exclaimed againſt publickly and privately by one that heard them not: And I do believe he was angered by more than two. For he is one that makes union to Chriſt, our having this Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon us, and our being juſtified by it to be given us in way of reward of ſomething done by us; and he is the man that makes the ſtate of Believers to be undecided and in ſuſpenſe during this Life. Both which Errors are damning; the former in its Nature and direct tendency; the latter in its Grounds and Principles. And whether he do not in truth diſown the imputation of our Sins unto Chriſt, and of his Righteouſneſs unto us, it is like if he live the VVorld will ſee more fully; for he hath given ſuch pregnant indications thereof as do amount to at leaſt juſt cauſe of jealouſie. But touching theſe things he thought it beſt to keep ſilence, and to fix his nails where he thought he had better advantage.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:94055:39"/>
            <p>The one Point is, <hi>pag.</hi> 7. That <hi>the Incarnation of Chriſt is no part of his Humiliation.</hi> As to the truth of it as there laid down, I ſhall ſay little more, knowing it cannot be overthrown. The whole ſtreſs of the matter lyes in thoſe two words, <hi>Incarnation</hi> and <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation,</hi> how they are taken. If the former be taken largely, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing Chriſts taking both our Nature and the common ſinleſs Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of it, together with his being in the form of a ſervant, and made under the Law, I know not why it ſhould be denyed to be a part of his Humiliation. But if it be taken ſtrictly for his dwelling in Fleſh, or Humane Nature, comprehending under it both the act of aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the relation or union ariſing and effected thereby between the Humane Nature ſo aſſumed, and the Perſon of the Son of God who did aſſume it; neither the one nor the other of theſe, neither the act of aſſuming, nor the Union of the two Natures effected by it may be allowed to be any part of Chriſt's Humiliation. For <hi>Humiliation</hi> is not in this argument to be taken laxly and improperly for any thing which hath Goodneſs or Grace in it, as God's beholding things in Heaven and in Earth, is ſaid to be an humbling of himſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.6. So Chriſt might have been ſaid to humble himſelf, though he had never been Incarnate. But in this ſubject <hi>Humiliation</hi> ought to be taken preciſely, for that which is proper and peculiar to the ſecond Perſon in the Trinity, which the Apoſtle calls his being <hi>in the form of a Servant,</hi> or rather his <hi>being made under the Law.</hi> Between which there may be conceived ſome difference; for Chriſt is now in his ſtate of Exaltation <hi>Gods Servant,</hi> but he is not now <hi>under the Law,</hi> as he was in the days of his Fleſh and Frailty. And taking theſe words thus, it is far from being a ſingular conceit of mine, that the Incarnation of Chriſt is not a part of his humiliation. Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> not only ſaith expreſly, Chriſt's aſſuming the Humane Nature, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not properly be ſaid to be a part of his Humiliation, but gives his reaſon for it, <hi>of Juſtif. ch.</hi> 17. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. and makes the Title of that Chapter to be this, <hi>Chriſt that he might taken on him the guilt of ſin, was made man:</hi> Whence it is evident that in his Judgment (which is alſo the current Judgment of all Chriſtians) Chriſt's becoming Man was not the effect of the guilt of ſin being on him, but the way of his becoming capable to have our guilt imputed to him. I ſuppoſe none will imagin that Chriſt had been in a ſtate of Humiliation if our guilt had not been upon him. Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> is as expreſs as expreſs can be to the ſame
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:94055:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>purpoſe. <hi>Marrow of Div. l.</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> 20. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3, 4. Mr. <hi>Norton</hi> againſt <hi>Pinchion, Part.</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 205. hath theſe words, <hi>Incarnation is not a Mediatorly or Office-Act, but an Act conſtituting the perſon called to that Office.</hi> Mr. <hi>Samuel Stone</hi> (a Divine of very exquiſite judgment and acuteneſs, and one ſo far from being an <hi>Antinomian,</hi> that he wrote againſt ſome of their Tenets, as I gather from Mr. <hi>Baxters Script. Goſp. def. l.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 73.) hath theſe words, <hi>Prin. of Orac of God,</hi> part 1. ch. 17 <hi>q.</hi> 2. <hi>What is Chriſts humiliation?</hi> Anſw. <hi>The abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt, whereby he became ſubject to Divine Juſtice to ſatisfie for our offences, and to merit Life and Happineſs. This abaſement pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth his Incarnation and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction. His Incarnation is therefore no part of his humiliation.</hi> And in his following explication he ſaith, <hi>The ſtate of abaſement falls upon the Son of God incarnate, his Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is one part of his fitneſs to redeem, and hence the Son of God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate before his humiliation in order of Nature, being the ſubject of humiliation. Hence the humiliation is aſcribed to the whole Perſon.</hi> Laſtly, ſince the preaching of theſe Sermons, an underſtanding Perſon tells me that that eminent Servant of Chriſt now in glory, Mr. <hi>John Collins</hi> delivered the very ſame thing, and being taxed for it by one who would not receive ſatisfaction from him, the matter was brought to Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> who readily declared himſelf to concur in his judgment with Mr. <hi>Collins.</hi> It is true, Divines commonly ſay Chriſt was humbled in his Conception. So beſides others, Mr. <hi>Alexander Richardſon, Ames, Stone,</hi> who yet hold that his Incarnation was no part of his Humiliation, and that in good conſiſtency with themſelves, and with the Truth. For Chriſt's Incarnation is one thing, his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception is another: By the one he became Man, by the other the Son of Man; the former implies only his participation of the Nature, the other together with the nature, the manner, and way of his partaking thereof; though ſtill in Chriſt they did concur and co-exiſt. Beſides there is a difference between ſaying Chriſt humbled himſelf <hi>in</hi> his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and ſaying his <hi>being conceived</hi> was part of his Humiliation. The former I readily aſſent to; for there were many circumſtances of great abaſement attended not only his Birth, but his very Conception. But as to the latter I would not ſo crudely aſſert it without ſome explication. For that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> conceived him, is agreed on by all Chriſtians; nor do I ſee reaſon to diſſent from that of <hi>Ames,</hi> That the Humane Nature was really related to <hi>Mary</hi> as to its cauſe.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:94055:40"/>But yet I do not remember that I have met with it in any judicious Writer, that <hi>Mary</hi> was a cauſe either of Chriſt's Incarnation, or of his Humiliation. And for my own part I would chuſe to refer Chriſts Conception (taken preciſely as abſtracted from all the afflictive or eclipſing circumſtances of it) to the things that made him allyed in blood to us, and ſo a fit Perſon to ſtand and act as our Surety, rather than to his actual performing the work of Suretiſhip as antecedently ſtanding in that relation unto us. For as I do not think the precept of the Moral Law ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth us to be conceived, nor that the curſe of it doth inflict it on us as a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, ſo neither do I ſee that Chriſt's Conception was any part of his fulfilling that Law for us, either in the precept, or in the penalty of it. Nor do I think it any dangerous Hereſie to hold that it is not imputed to us any more than that his Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, and Interceſſion are not. And yet whatever there was in Chriſt's Conception, of his fulfilling the Law either in the precept, or in the curſe of it, I do look upon as a part of his Righteouſneſs which is imputed to us. But though there were circumſtances of great abaſement in Chriſt's Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet I can by no means aſſent to that which was again and again aſſerted at <hi>Pinners-Hall</hi> by him, who there oppoſed Chriſt's Incarnation being no part of his Humiliation, namely, <hi>That the Son of God was united to an Embrio.</hi> I do not herein tranſgreſs the Apoſtles rule, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19. I have ſeen the Notes of that Sermon taken by two Perſons, and have had this atteſted by at leaſt twice too. An <hi>Embrio</hi> is an unformed unorganized maſs or lump, not a perfect Humane Nature. To ſay that the Son of God did aſſume, or was united to ſuch a thing as an <hi>Embrio</hi> is a piece of Ignorant Blaſphemy. But alas, whither will the heat of oppoſition carry Men. That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reader may not think I am ſingular herein, he may look into Mr. <hi>Nortons, Ortho, Evang. ch.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 39.</p>
            <p>But what is the reaſon why Chriſt's Incarnation muſt needs be made a part of his humiliation? I ſuſpect there is a ſecret at the bottom of this matter. I doubt he diſcerns that if Chriſt's Incarnation be taken up and admitted to be a part of his humiliation, it puts an Engine into his hand to overthrow the imputation of Chriſt's humiliation unto us. For if one part of it be not imputed, it's eaſie infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, the reſt is not. And it is no difficult task to evince that the Incarnation of Chriſt is not imputed to us. But for that very reaſon I did, and ſtill do judge it neceſſary to be ſo expreſt in diſtinguiſhing between Chriſt's Incarnation and his Humiliation, and to declare the former not to be a part of the latter.</p>
            <p>The other point deeply reflected on, is <hi>pag.</hi> 22, 23, 24, 25. <hi>That Bilievers are as Righteous as Chriſt is, as he is their Surety.</hi> I heard it, and took it in firſt many Years agoe in a Sermon from that Reverend Man of God, my Honoured Father in Law, Mr. <hi>William Ben</hi> of <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> a Man ſo ſhining in Holineſs, ſo excelling in clearneſs of Goſpel-Light, and ſo abounding in Solid, Spiritual, Practical, Scriptural Notions, that I have not known many that have gone beyond him, few that equalled him. I have ſince conſidered, all that I have met with againſt it in Papiſts, Socinians, and their Followers: And am and was well aware that ſome Learned Men ſeem to decline owning it, but 'tis only in the ſenſe in which their Adverſaries mean it, and would infer it. Others ſeem to own it with certain limitations and explications. I no way doubt, but that, as by me deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, it will be found a Truth that will abide in ſtrength, and firmneſs, when all the Papiſts, Socinians, and Semiſocinians on Earth have broken their Teeth upon it. And this I ſay with an eye particularly to his Diſcourſes who ſo publickly
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:94055:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:94055:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:94055:42"/>quarrelled at it, in which by the account I had of them I could find nothing fit to be taken notice of. It is an eaſie thing to quote many that tax it as madneſs and blaſphemy to ſay Believers are equal with Chriſt, but they muſt be underſtood in a limited ſenſe, and as meaning ſuch an equality as interferes with Chriſt's Headſhip, and with his having the pre-eminence in all things. For taken abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, and in all reſpects it will not hold. Believers are Men equally with Chriſt, and they are juſtified from their ſin equally with Chriſt, for they are perfectly ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, and perfectly freed from the revenging Wrath of God in this Life, and from Condemnation. Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> though he be not for ſuch an imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, as others are, who are not Antinomians, as Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> Dr. <hi>Jacomb,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ant. Burgeſs,</hi> yet ſaith, <hi>God doth not only forgive to Perſons juſtified all their ſins, but doth alſo, even in like manner eſteem them themſelves, and accounts them in the ſame place as if they were altogether free from all manner of ſin both of commiſſion and omiſſion. Perinde aeſtimat e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>demque loco habet.</hi> What would this diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied Perſon have ſaid, if I had affirmed that <hi>we have a whole and unmaimed righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, againſt which God in his moſt exact juſtice cannot proceed; no more than he can call his own Son to a ſecond Death, or not accept his face, who is the righteouſneſs of God himſelf?</hi> Or if I had ſaid, that <hi>Mary under the Croſs was more juſt imputatively than Chriſt, which was alſo true of every Believer then living, when Chriſt was under the actual imputation of Sin.</hi> And that <hi>God looking on Believers through Chriſt ſeeth no more ſin (ſafely underſtood) than he ſeeth in him.</hi> The former are the words of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Mr. <hi>Cartwright againſt the Rhemiſts</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13. and the latter of Mr. <hi>Norton, Orth. Evang. ch.</hi> 14. <hi>pag.</hi> 324. I might multiply quotations to the ſame purpoſe. But to what end? I fear it is a diſlike and heart-hatred of ſtanding juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed and in it only, that lyes at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom in theſe oppoſitions. For the thing is evident in it ſelf (and I can hardly think any man is ſo forſaken of common underſtanding as to deny it) that if it be the ſame righteouſneſs in which Chriſt and we ſtand, he and we are ſo far as that righteouſneſs makes righteous, equally righteous: If it be the ſame righteouſneſs that is upon him and upon us, it muſt needs have the ſame effect as to making righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Let it be but owned and believed that it is Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, and not our own, either Faith or other Graces, or Obedience that we ſtand juſtified in before God, and what I have delivered muſt be owned, and is ſo, whether Men ſee it or not. But if Chriſt's Righteouſneſs be not upon us, if that be not the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly righteouſneſs in which we ſtand juſtified; it is then abſurd and monſtrous and blaſphemous, or whatever men that like not ſtanding in the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt pleaſe to call it, to ſay that imputatively we are as righteous as Chriſt is righteous as our Surety.</p>
            <p>It may be that ſome or other who do believe theſe things to be bleſſed and glorious Truths may think it had been better not to have ſpoken them out. I muſt crave leave in this to diſſent from them, I do not think that in ſuch a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject we ſhould at ſuch a time be mealy-mouthed. Had <hi>Luther, Zuinglius, Calvin, Zanchy,</hi> and others of the firſt Reformers been as faint and complying in their expreſſions, as ſome very great and good men then were; and as <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> himſelf for ſome time was, the precious truths of God had been greatly obſcured, and the Light thereof not propagated down to us, as it is at this day.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
